<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two treatises concerning the matter of the Engagement. The first of an unknown author, excepting against Mr. Dureus Considerations for the taking of the Engagement, to shew the unsatisfactoriness thereof. : The second of Mr. Dureus maintaining the satisfactoriness of his considerations against the unknown authors exceptions.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74854</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E615_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC P1074</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">50805949</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 50805949</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165758</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74854)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165758)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 94:E615[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two treatises concerning the matter of the Engagement. The first of an unknown author, excepting against Mr. Dureus Considerations for the taking of the Engagement, to shew the unsatisfactoriness thereof. : The second of Mr. Dureus maintaining the satisfactoriness of his considerations against the unknown authors exceptions.</title>
                  <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 61 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Clowes for Richard Wodenothe ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At head of t.p.: Numb. 3.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dury, John, 1596-1680. --  Considerations concerning the present Engagement.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165758:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO TREATISES Concerning the matter of the ENGAGEMENT.</p>
            <p>The firſt of an unknown Author, excepting againſt Mr. <hi>Dureus</hi> Conſiderations for the taking of the ENGAGEMENT, to ſhew the unſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs thereof.</p>
            <p>The ſecond of Mr. <hi>Dureus</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the ſatisfactorineſs of his Conſiderations againſt the unknown Authors exceptions.</p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> J. Clowes <hi>for</hi> Richard Wodenothe <hi>at the</hi> Star <hi>under St.</hi> Peters <hi>Church in</hi> Cornhil, 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:165758:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165758:2"/>
            <head>The firſt <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> whereof the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle was, Mr. <hi>Dureus</hi> his friend unſatisfied, or an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to a Paper publiſhed in print by Mr. <hi>John Dureus,</hi> entituled, <hi>(Conſiderations concerning the preſent En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, whether it may be lawfully entred into yea, or no?)</hi> affectionately preſented to the ſerious conſideration both of Mr. <hi>Dureus</hi> and all others that deſire to give, and receive ſatisfaction concerning the truth.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Letter of <hi>November</hi> 27. ſent to your friend for ſatisfaction of his Conſcience (ſcrupling the taking of the Engagement) is come into theſe parts, and, as may be conjectured, into all parts of the Kingdom, ſo that it ſeems your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thoughts were to make every Reader ſo far your friend, as to help him in caſe of like irreſolution. You obſerve in your ſelect friend to whom you make your ſpecial ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, that he hath been alwayes affected to the Common cauſe of Liberty, againſt the deſigns of tyranny, upon which your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will ſoon obſerve, that ſuch have their heſitancys in this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and it is obſerved not by a few, that almoſt all ſuch have their ſcruples, and almoſt onely ſuch. Others (on what Principles I ſhall forbear to ſpeak) readily enough for the moſt part enter up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it; which confeſſion of yours, ſeconded with the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of others, doth much amuſe your reader, that you ſhould paſs ſo heavy a cenſure on all that remaining unſatisfied, as yet ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165758:3"/>having your own atteſtation, that they cordially purſue that which in your thoughts is the end of this, and all other pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Engagements; namely, the intrinſecal good of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. To which alſo they are ready to ſubſcribe, not with the hand onely, but with the heart likewiſe, if they were once per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that Covenants and publick promiſes, bind not at all to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental forms, (as you ſtile them) when yet they are made by publick authority, that did impoſe them the very Letter, or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſuch Covenants or Engagements. Somewhat I ſhall make bold to ſpeak to your Conſiderations, to let you ſee how far in the thoughts of many, they fall ſhort of carrying your Queſtion in the affirmative, in which I ſhall endeavour to keep me to the principal heads, that tediouſneſs may not be your trouble.</p>
            <p>Your firſt work is to reconcile this Engagement, to the Oath of Allegiance, and the National Covenant, attempting to make it good, that they are not oppoſite, and in reference hereunto, you lay down as a State maxime, that the <hi>obligation of King and Subjects are mutual, and muſt needs ſtand and fall together, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the condition by which they are begotten, is kept or broken; which is nothing elſe but the Law, according to which he and his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects agree,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>that he ſhall be their King, and they his Subjects.</hi> When this is yielded, yet herein you fall ſhort, that you do not produce that Law (to which he ſtands obliged) that doth declare this or that act of his, to be a full forfeiture of truſt, and <hi>ipſo facto</hi> inflict that penalty of the loſs of all his regalities, and diſobligation of his Subjects; If ſuch a law were but produced and a tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on proved, it would perhaps ſerve to quiet many minds. Mr. <hi>Cook</hi> (if I miſtake not) anſwering the objection, why no Law was made in ſuch caſe againſt Kings, inſtead of producing a Law; onely gives in the anſwer of <hi>Solon,</hi> why in his Laws he omitted the puniſhment of <hi>Parricides,</hi> freely confeſſing that as in the one, ſo in the other a Law was wanting; Thoſe againſt whom the late war hath frequently been avowed to be made, have alſo Laws with large penalties in caſe of tranſgreſſion made againſt them, <hi>(viz.)</hi> all ſuch as are found Counſellors in evil, or as ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Officers are Agents in it; which <hi>page</hi> 13. you ſeem to grant to be good ſecurity, and what hath been ſtill ſaid for the immunity of Kings in this Nation (who act nothing as Kings
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165758:3"/>in their own perſons, but by ſubordinate Agents) You though an <hi>Alienigena</hi> cannot be ignorant, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> but you go on and tell us wherein the King hath been unſaithful to his truſt, even to the abſolving of his people <hi>pſo facto</hi> from their Allegiance; <hi>it hath been</hi> (you ſay as you ſuppoſe) <hi>a perpetual cuſtome in this Nation, for the Commons at all times to ask and propoſe the making of the Lawes, and for the Lords and King to give conſent thereunto;</hi> and after a few words of Explication you make your Application; <hi>If the King then ſhould ſet himſelf wilfully to be above this reaſon of the Nation, which is the onely Original of the Law, and refuſe obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately the Lawes which they ſhall chooſe to be ſetled: he puts himſelf</hi> ipſo facto <hi>out of the capacity of being a King any more unto them; and if this can be made out to have been the way wherein the late King ſet himſelf, and that it was the deſign of the Houſe of Lords, to uphold and inable him to follow that way, it is evident that ſo far as he did by that means actually unking himſelf: ſo far alſo they that aſſiſted him in that deſign, did unlord themſelvs in the ſtate thereof.</hi> In which ſentence of yours all readers, when they compare with it what you lay down for a rule <hi>pag.</hi> 10. may eaſily wonder at your great forgetfulneſs Here you judge definitively in the higheſt way of the rights which ſupreme powers have over us, and give in your verdict above all (that I know) hath ever been charged upon them; and there you ſay, <hi>for my own part I have taken this to be a rule whereby all private men, (ſuch as I am) as Chriſtians ought to walk unblameablely under the Superiour powers of this world; namely, that it doth not belong to us to judge definitively of the rights which the Supreme powers in this world pretend to have to their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> farther you ſay; <hi>It is no part of our Chriſtian profeſſion to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Judges of the great ones of this world, in reſpect of their rights and pretentions to power, for we are to behave our ſelves as ſpiritual men in this world by the rule of our profeſſion, and as ſtrangers and pilgrims therein.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Which paſſages how you will be able to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile I cannot reach: And your miſtake of the Cuſtomes of this Nation (which ſo punctually you undertake to lay down,) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals your forgetfulneſs of your ſelf, ſo that here indeed (at leaſt) you appear a ſtranger; the Lawes are well known to have had ſtill their firſt riſe indifferently from-Lords and Commons, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times from the one, ſometimes from the other: the buſineſs of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165758:4"/>money onely excepted, which alwayes with us begins with the Commons. And I ſuppoſe (however it fares with the Lords) Kings have not often been found guilty in refuſal of their aſſent to Bills of Subſidies, Taxes, Pole-money, Tonnage, poundage, &amp;c. And that it hath been a perpetual Cuſtome for Kings and Lords to aſſent to all that the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons have propoſed, is boldly affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; endeavouring to perſwade your reader, that not only <hi>de jure</hi> it ought to be ſo (which ſure at ſome conference or other, the Commons for prevention of ſo many diſputes and reaſonings, would have charged upon the Lords) but that <hi>de facto</hi> it hath been ſo, when all that know any thing of the Cuſtome of this Nation, very well know the contrary, that the Lords have given their aſſent or diſſent to Bills, (ſent from the Commons) accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as they have judged it moſt expedient, and often ſent them back with amendments, according as in their ſenſe they have judged them moſt meet to paſs as Lawes; and that Kings inſtead of yielding aſſent to Bills ſent from Lords and Commons, have often times onely returned a <hi>Le Roy aviſera;</hi> which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times (as I have heard from ſingular Patriots) hath turned to the great happineſs of the Nation.</p>
            <p>And as you pretend to have cleared the meaning of the Oath of Allegiance (which was made in our own age) by the conſent as you ſay of all ages, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> ſo you go about a further explanation of it, by the third Article of the Covenant, which is not oppoſite to the Oath of Allegiance; <hi>and this obligeth</hi> (you ſay) <hi>to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Kings Perſon and Anthority conditionally, and with a limitation onely; namely, in the preſervation and defence of the true Religion and Libertyes of the Kingdom;</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Which Comment of yours upon that Article of the Covenant (turning <hi>In</hi> into <hi>If,</hi> to make a condition of it, and changing the whole current of the words from our ſelves to the Kings, ſo that they ſhould be meant of the Kings preſervation of Liberty and Religion, and not our own (when all before and after mentioned, is our work and not his) is ſuch, ſo forced and ſtrained, that it will abide the cenſure of no indifferent and unbiaſſed reader, and is fully e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough contradicted in thoſe words which immediatly follow, which you prudently conceale; <hi>That the world may bear witneſs with our Conſciences of our loyalty, and that we have no thoughts</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:165758:4"/>or intentions to diminiſh his Majeſties juſt power and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>It was (as is well known) frequently charged upon the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that what ever their intendments were, for Religion and the publick Liberties; yet they had an evil eye on his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, not brooking his power and greatneſs, which was as fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently diſavowed, as a ſcandal not ſufferable; and in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for this very end this ſolemn appeal was inſerted, in which we have firſt an acknowledgment that his Majeſty ſtood veſted with juſt power and greatneſs, and ſo no ſuch forfeiture made as before you mention; And ſecondly a ſerious proteſtation made that we have no intention to diminiſh it, but as we reſolve to preſerve Religion and Liberty: ſo we oblige our ſelves to loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty to the Kings perſon, and Authority, and from all thoughts or intentions to diminiſh his power and greatneſs, which is the true and clear meaning of it. Upon mention of the Lawes and Liberties of the Kingdom, you ſay <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
               <hi>The King either refractori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caſting them off, or ſeeming to yield unto them in ſuch a way, that no truſt could be given him, that he would keep what he yielded unto, the Parliament did actually lay him aſide, and voted that no more addreſſes ſhould be made unto him;</hi> Where you ſeem unreſolved whether it were guilt in his Majeſty, or jealouſie in the Houſes that occaſioned thoſe Votes? Whether the King did actually deſerve them, or whether there was onely jealouſie, that he would render himſelf worthy of them? The ſuſpected Wife <hi>Numb.</hi> 5. might not be caſt off till her guilt was proved, though ſome are pleaſed to put Kings and Wives, both in one condition, to be caſt off meerly <hi>ad placitum,</hi> the one by the husband, the other by the people: which (as to Kings) you ſeem not to judge unreaſonable; Then followes in your Letter <hi>from which time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, he was no more an object of your Oath of Allegiance,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
               <hi>but to be looked upon as a private man.</hi> Yes ſure when the Parliament had againe voted addreſſes to him, <hi>ejus eſt tollere, cujus eſt ponere,</hi> If the Parliament have a legiſtative, they have alſo le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtranſlative or repealing power: if Votes can ſet free, then Votes can reoblige: you go on, and ſay to an indifferent eye, <hi>it,</hi> (namely the Engagement) <hi>may be thought ſo far from being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the true ſence of either, that it may be rather a confirmation
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165758:5"/>of the ground for which both the Oath of Allegiance, and third Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the National Covenant was then binding;</hi> for confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of which, you ſay, <hi>this or that outward form of Government is wholly accidental, no wayes eſſential to any Nation in the world; and therefore is alterable in reſpect of forms, as is moſt expedient for their exigent neceſſities, but to be governed by Lawes, and to have the uſe of the true Religion, and of the National freedom, is abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary and eſſential to the being of a Common-wealth,</hi> paſſing by that State Paradox, that to have the uſe of the true Religion and of the National freedom, is abſolutely neceſſary and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to the being of a Common-wealth: ſo there neither is nor ever was any Common-wealth out of <hi>Criſtendome,</hi> nor many in it, (a few only having that happineſs,) This takes wholly for granted, that all our Oaths have reſpected barely the <hi>eſſe</hi> of the Nation, or that which (you ſay) was called the Kingdom, when all that reade them muſt confeſs, that they had immediat reſpect to the <hi>bene eſſe,</hi> in their preſent conſtitution, and external admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration; we ſwear not barely to the remote end (which is the intrinſecal good as you ſpeak, of the Nation) but to the meanes which (in the judgement of thoſe which you ſometimes call the reaſon of the Nation) had a direct tendency to it, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> namely the continuance of Monarchy in the preſent line, any change attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by men, neceſſarily in humane reaſon, tending to the Nations danger, if not ruin and deſtruction. Conſult I pray you caſuiſts, when the oath in the expreſs letter looks at the means, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to lead to an end, whether it be enough for the party ſworn to intend alone the end, in contradiction to the means, which was the matter of the Oath.</p>
            <p>If I come to a Garriſon and be there queſtioned, whether I come from the enemies quarters yea, or no? May I deny upon Oath that I came from thence, when indeed I did? ſatisfying my ſelf with this, that I will not betray the Garriſon where I am, the queſtion whence I came being onely accidental, the ſafety of the Garriſon is the thing the Oath onely intended; and to this in ſuch an Oath I anſwer, Inquire whether this be not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury?</p>
            <p>This evaſion to eye the end and not look at accidentall forms (as you call them) will facilitate a way to any Oath, and as eaſily
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:165758:5"/>diſobliege, rendring the Oath vain as ſoon as it is entered; Thus it had been ſafe to have entered the Canon Oath (preſcribed by the Convocation in the year that this <hi>Parliament</hi> did commence) for the eſtabliſhment of the Hierarchy in Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Deans, Deans and Chapters, Chancellours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Seeing we might have entered into it (how oppoſite ſoever our judgements were againſt it) and then have avoided it, explaining our ſelves that we ſwore to the end, namely Church-Government, &amp; order for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick edification, without reſpect to external forms, which is acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental; which Government being in our judgment beſt ſetled, in an Independant Congregational way (as ſome think) or in a Presbyterial Claſſical way (as others) this Oath thus interpreted, is ſo far from engaging to Prelacy, that it engageth againſt it, ſo far from binding to a non conſent of the change and alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it (which was the letter of the Oath) that it binds us to a vigorous endeavour of change and alteration; thus alſo all Covenanters are diſobliged from the ſecond Article in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant (which is to the extirpation of Prelacy, as there explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) in caſe they believe (as many do) that Church-Government is beſt ſettled, and the Churches edification beſt provided for in ſuch a conſtitution, and ſo Covenanting againſt it in the letter of the Covenant, they Covenant for it in the end, which you ſay is onely to be heeded. Neither can any State this way find any ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity in any Oath preſcribed, all may enter; and then evade with this ſhift of the intrinſecal good of the Common-wealth of the Nation, and plead that the neceſſity of the publick good calls to the tranſgreſſion and contradiction of it: Thus <hi>Zedeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> might have freed himſelf from his Oath of fealty to <hi>Nebucad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezar;</hi> it being (as he might have pleaded) againſt the intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecal good of that Nation, that ſtrangers ſhould rule over them, and they be made a Province to <hi>Babylon,</hi> his Oath to ſerve him would have ſtrongly engaged to a revolt from him. And the Oath of the Elders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> (thus underſtood) had been null in the very taking of it, evidently tending to the publick dammage, of which the Commons of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were very ſenſible, as appears in their exceptions taken againſt the Elders, for entring into it. <hi>Saul</hi> in the act which brought a three years famine upon <hi>Iſrael</hi> (if this divinity might take place) had done a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165758:6"/>work ſingularly commendable, ſeeing it was his zeal to the houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> which alone moved him (againſt the letter of his Covenant) to the ſlaughter of thoſe perſons, even the publick good ſo evidently damnified, and endangered by their abode in the midſt of the people. <hi>Sauls</hi> ſlaughter of theſe <hi>Gibeonites</hi> had been as praiſe-worthy as <hi>Davids</hi> (his ſucceſſors) ſlaughter of the <hi>Jebuſites,</hi> the publick good being <hi>Sauls</hi> end (the Holy-Ghoſt bearing witneſs) as well as <hi>Davids;</hi> and what good the preſent State can reap by this Engagement (your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation being once admitted) I believe you know not which way to demonſtrate; the engagers may ſay, they will be true and faithful to the Common-wealth, as now eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without King or houſe of Lords, in their endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſh a King and houſe of Lords; which they may think moſt tends to the honour and peace of it.</p>
            <p>You go on to anſwer a further Objection of your friends, that <hi>in the third Article of the Covenant, he is ſworn to preſerve, the Rights and Priviledges of Parliament,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 
               <hi>amongſt which this is one, that therein ſhould be a houſe of Lords diſtinct from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; and this another, that all the Members of the Commons ſhould ſit and vote freely; for when he ſwore, he meant a Parliament ſo conſtituted and no other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer of which, you firſt confeſs, and then endeavour to avoid, and if you did avoid as clearly, as you do confeſs ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, you would give more ſatisfaction; you confeſs that <hi>theſe are Priviledges, that the intention of the Covenant, was to preſerve theſe, and that now ſuch intentions cannot be proſecuted;</hi> which confeſſion alone, is enough to create a bigger ſcruple in your friend, then the whole force of all which yet hath appeared in your anſwer can wipe off. Your way to avoid is, <hi>that your friend did what in him lay when time and place was, according to his Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to prevent theſe breaches, and ſo cannot be accuſed of the infringement thereof; for when a fatal neceſſity of State,</hi> (as you ſay) <hi>in the courſe of divine juſtice with a power irreſiſtible, not onely to men of private, but to all that were in publick vocations, did bring about that change upon the Parliament, no particular mens engagements were conſiderable.</hi> This no doubt is a clear juſtification of your friend, one mans ſin pollutes not another, when by oppoſing, and in his place withſtanding, he keeps him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165758:6"/>from guilty participation. But in this excuſe of him from breach of Covenant, in the infringement of Parliament Priviledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, you do plainly charge that irreſiſtible power (which you ſpeak of) with it, He is therefore innocent becauſe he did what in him lay, in his place to prevent this change; thoſe then can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be innocent, that being intereſted and obliged in the ſame Covenant, did yet with ſuch a power (as you mention) work it; Neither can that ſuppoſed fatal neceſſity of State (which your anſwer ſpeaks of) acquit that power from breach of their Covenant in ſuch confeſſed infringement of Parliament-Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of the Kingdom (as elſe-where you call it) ſaw no ſuch neceſſity as your Paper takes for granted, but with high re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions oppoſed when the power was at their doors, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs in imminent danger, both Houſes judged the way that they were upon, to be the way moſt conducing to the States ſafety; and it was their buſineſs and no other powers, in ſuch caſe to give judgement. And in caſe this neceſſity had been real, and not imaginary or pretended; yet it were no ſufficient plea for ſuch a tranſgreſsion. <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the Elders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> underſtood no ſuch State-divinity, to break Covenant on ſuch grounds, much leſs on ſuch pretences. Much might have been ſaid by them to have neceſſitated a breach with thoſe <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> with whom they had entred Covenant; <hi>Gibeon</hi> was one of their Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Cities, and of danger to be poſſeſſed by ſuch an enemy: or to have him ſtill in their howels to lay claim to it; the Land was <hi>Iſraels</hi> by the gift of God, and too narrow for themſelves in ſuch multitudes to inhabit, there was no reaſon that the fat and the ſweet ſhould be devoured and eaten up by ſtrangers. The arguments of <hi>Egypt</hi> againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> might well here have been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up by <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when there falls out any war, they will joyn unto the enemies.</p>
            <p>Theſe Reaſons or the like of equal or greater ſtrength <hi>Saul</hi> doubtleſs ſaw, when he ſought to ſlay them (not out of any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ſpleen but) in his zeal to the houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and of <hi>Judah;</hi> but none of theſe did ſway with thoſe Covenanters, and God himſelf acquits them from any miſtake in the Obligation of that their Covenant, in his proceeding againſt the houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165758:7"/>obſerved, when private men ſwear to their hurt, they muſt not change, when States ſwear they may not change: there is no ſecurity without God from any danger; it is more ſafe to keep with God, though ſeemingly we run upon peri, I then to quit the wayes of God deſerting him for prevention to ſpeak the faireſt, theſe reaſonings come from unbelief.</p>
            <p>You go on, and ſay, <hi>You ſee what pinches your friend: He thinks that they that made the change broke the Covenant,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> 
               <hi>and if he engage under this change as is deſired, he thinks he breaks the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant alſo.</hi> To which you anſwer,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That they who made the change will plead for themſelves, that they are not guilty of any breach of Covenant notwithſtanding the change.</hi> But this you leave to them to juſtifie; And ſeeing you will not juſtifie them, I ſhall not ſtand to implead them, your Reader being fully ſatisfied, that your own pen in your former confeſſion hath already done it.</p>
            <p>Secondly you anſwer, <hi>For the conſequence your friends make from the taking of the Engagement to a breach of the Covenant, it doth not at all follow to your underſtanding; for the direct and plain matter of the Engagement, binds him onely to procure the good of the Common-wealth as now it ſtands; and becauſe at all times and in all conſtitutions thereof, he is bound to do this no leſs by the Covenant it ſelf, then by the Engagement; therefore his taking of this, to this effect, can be no breach of that,</hi> which you endeavour to make good by a comment upon the words of the Engagement; <hi>for the negative words, without a King and a houſe of Lords in the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, may</hi> (as you ſay) <hi>be properly and moſt obviouſly taken, as an explication of the words now eſtabliſhed, immediatly going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and not an abſolute abnegation of the things looked upon truly, and as in themſelves,</hi> with more words to the ſame purpoſe, which gloſs of yours calls for ſome obſervation, and well deſerves ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, neceſſarily implying a high charge of ſuch inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateneſs, in the heads of thoſe that did deviſe, and in the power of thoſe that do impoſe this Engagement, of which none can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that they are guilty.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They knew, that all the Subjects of this Nation, ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore engaged to the intrinſecal good of this Common-wealth, (as by the dictates of nature, the obligation of reaſon, ſelf-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165758:7"/>which each one knows is wrapt up in the publick, ſo alſo) by an oath preſcribed by their power ſince they entred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, reaching doubtleſs thus far, and (as ſome conjecture) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended further, that which was already done to their hands (as you ſay) by ſo many Oaths and Covenants, which themſelves alſo ſince their inveſtiture in power had done, they will not do over again, in words not at all further obliging, but onely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexing, amuſing and inſnaring.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They know that the Engagement in this ſenſe will nothing tend to their eſtabliſhment, as before hath been evidenced; yea they know with this gloſs upon it, it hath a full tendency to their further danger, not a few being perſwaded (how erroneouſly ſoever) that the publick good is beſt provided for, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Engagement anſwered in their oppoſition, all of which is ſo clear to every eye, that it could not be hid from thoſe that impoſed this Engagement, ſo that none can think that they would trouble the conſciences of ſo many thouſands in ſuch a needleſs way to their own <hi>non</hi>-benefit, yea to their further peril. If the Covenant mentioning Monarchy in a King, do tye us to a republick in a State, (as you before affirm) then the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment mentioning a republick without King or houſe of Lords, may tye us to Monarchy by the ſame reaſon.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This gloſs carrys a full contradiction in it ſelf, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> you ſay, <hi>theſe words without King &amp; houſe of Lords, may be properly and moſt obviouſly taken, as an explication of the word [as now eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed] immediatly going before, and not an abſolute negation of the things themſelves;</hi> when as thoſe words, <hi>as now eſtabliſhed,</hi> do fully imply that abnegation of Kings &amp; Lords, which you there men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>now</hi> being an adverb of time, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>Engagement</hi> muſt needs ſtand in full oppoſition to the face of things in form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er adminiſtrations, it cannot look on the Common-weale ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractively as the ſame, in all revolutions and junctures of times, but as it now ſtands in a preſent different poſture, <hi>as now</hi> is a full contradiction to your ſenſe, <hi>as ever.</hi> And I pray you conſider, whether the powers now eſtabliſhed without King and Lords, have not voted down both King and Lords, as uſeleſs and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous; and therfore <hi>now eſtabliſhed,</hi> is no other then an abne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165758:8"/>of Kings and Lords heretofore eſtabliſhed; therefore your friend being in this pinched, is not yet eaſed.</p>
            <p>You go on as diſcerning that what is ſaid will not hold. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> 
               <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe</hi> (ſay you) <hi>that in your apprehenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of matters, this Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth materially ſettle ſome thing in the Common-wealth, which is contrary to the intention which you had in taking the Covenant; yet I ſay that by giving your aſſent thereunto, as matters now ſtand, you break not at all your Covenant, becauſe your obligation to thoſe matters by vertue of the Covenant, was extinguiſhed before you were called upon to take this Engagement; now that which is extinct and made void, cannot be ſaid to oblige any more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſuppoſition of yours, is wholly yielded by others, that it is in full oppoſition to the Covenant and other Oaths, (and ſo all your labour loſt in endeavouring to reconcile them) and this which you now bring, is onely held out for a Plea to carry it in the affirmative, that the Engagement may be entered, <hi>malè res agitur, cum tot opus eſt remediis,</hi> is wont to be ſaid; for your Propoſition, that that which is extinct and made void, can no more oblige, muſt be acknowledged as truth; with its juſt limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, provided that thoſe concerned in the Oath, have no hand in the extinguiſhing of it, for their own diſobligation. <hi>David</hi> was bound by Covenant unto <hi>Jonathan,</hi> and his ſeed after him, had he conſented to the death of <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> the Son of <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> the matter of the Covenant had then been extinct, and yet <hi>David</hi> had been guilty of the breach of it; for your aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that the matter of the Covenant as to the third Article, is extinct, it <hi>being impoſſible in nature to preſerve the Kings life now it is cut off: and the houſe of Lords now it is put down,</hi> I ſhall not ſtand upon that maxime, <hi>the King never dyes,</hi> and ſo though the man be cut off, yet the King remains and may be preſerved; if you pleaſe to look into the Preface of the Covenant, there we profeſſed, <hi>That we had before our eyes the glory of God, and the advancement of the Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, the Honour and Happineſs of the Kings Maieſty, and his Poſterity.</hi> As we dare not ſhut out the Glory of God, the advancement of the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt: no more dare we wholly ſhut out the Kings poſterity from the Covenant; for the Lords
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165758:8"/>though they ſit not as Lords in Parliament, yet ſtill they are as Lords, and in a capacity for actual admiſſion. You ſay, <hi>they may have a title to this right, &amp; yet be obliged, even for preſervation of that right to ſuſpend it for a time,</hi> and many I ſay are well ſatisfied, that they for ſuch end do ſuſpend, and yet dare not engage to an oppoſition of it.</p>
            <p>You yet go one ſtep higher, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> and ſo you are at the higheſt in this particular, being willing to perſwade your friend, <hi>that we are ſo far from being barred from the Engagement by the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, particularly the third Article of it, that we are engaged to it; if the third Article of the National Covenant concerning Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parl. be yet in force in any degree,</hi> you ſay, <hi>then it binds us to preſerve the Priviledges of Parliament that now are, as well as thoſe that then were.</hi> To which I ſay, I know no ſuch diſtinction of Priviledges that are, and were, Parliament Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges being alwayes the ſame, admitting of no ſuch chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, though we, have no more Parliament actually exiſting, then in Winter-time we have Roſes; yet as the properties of a Roſe are ſtill the ſame in all ſeaſons, ſo are the Priviledges of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: and if there be any remainder of Priviledges in actual being (as you contend) then the third Article that binds to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them, binds us to perfect them. A Phyſician cannot preſerve unleſs he recover ſtrength in his weak Patient: You conclude this firſt general piece of yours with hopes that your friend will find no cauſe to ſcruple any further at it, whereas others think that you have ſmall cauſe of hopes that you have eaſed him of any of his Scruples.</p>
            <p>In your ſecond part, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> you make it your buſineſs to ſatisfie your friend, concerning the power whereby this preſent Engagement is tendered, which he takes to be very doubtful, <hi>as a power un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully uſurped, as alſo whether by this Engagement he ſhall make himſelf acceſſorie to this uſurpation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, Inſtead of clearing their title as juſt and lawful, and acquitting it from uſurpation, you make it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to inquire and determine concerning it; holding out (as you ſay) <hi>the rule whereby you order your converſation,</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing him ready (as it ſeems) in all things to make you his precedent; in which way of yours, how diſſonant
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165758:9"/>you are from your ſelf, and how far you have been found a tranſgreſſour of your own rule, hath formerly been ſhewed; yet (whereſoever the guilt lyes) the tranſgreſſion by you is ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated to that height, as to be <hi>one the greateſt Characters of the Spirit of Antichriſt that exalts himſelf above all that is called God; and wherein</hi> (ſay you) <hi>hath he done this more remarkably to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Magiſtrates who are called Gods among men, then by exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf over them, to become a judge of all their rights and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions to power in this world?</hi> where I pray you take into your ſerious conſideration, whether this ſpirit (that great Character of the ſpirit of Antichriſt) doth manifeſt it ſelf in the man of ſin, in a careful enquirie and diligent ſearch to finde out to what power it is, that he juſtly owes ſubjection, and is to bind himſelf by Oath of feoalty, for faithfulneſs: or rather in his peremptory determinations of the forfeiture of right, in thoſe that before were poſſeſſed of an undoubted title, and diſobliging Subjects from their obedience, and to whom this Character of his doth moſt belong, whether to your friend or ſome other, I leave you ſadly to conſider. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> Yet after a long debate of the inconſiſtency of the duty which <hi>God</hi> appointed ſubjects, with the ſcrupuloſity of this queſtion, you are pleaſed to allow your friend <hi>in the judgement of diſcretion as a member of this Common-wealth, and concerned in the publick welfare thereof to look upon ſuperiours, to ſee how they pretend to ſtand; that is by what apparent right, and with what viſible power they poſſeſs their place;</hi> Which liberty of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you yet allow with this reſervation, that he ſuffer not his conſcience to follow the dictates of it, for ſo he is bound up in that which follows, which yet you call the bounds of Chriſtian liberty and rationality. Sure to me, blind obedience is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before ſuch uſe of light, that when I believe I ſee my way, I have no allowance to walk in it: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> You help us by the way with ſome hints how we may judge who is our Superiour; Such a Superiour (I ſuppoſe) you mean whom we muſt engage to ſerve with faithfulneſs; and this we may judge ſay you, <hi>by the dictates of ſenſe, reaſon and conſcience; Senſe, will ſhew him who is actually in poſſeſsion of all power, and places of Government over him, and by this he will perceive under whom he doth ſtand; Reaſon will ſhew what he who is over him, pretends unto, whether yea, or no his pretences are
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:165758:9"/>backed with power, to maintain his right againſt all advarſaries therein; and whether yea, or no, the uſe of that power be limitted by Law, or left wholly to his own will without Law and conſcience will ſhew, that he to whom God hath committed the plenary admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of publick affairs with unconfrontable power, is Gods Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent over the ſociety of thoſe to whom his adminiſtration doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it ſelf, either by vertue of a contract, which makes a Law, or by vertue of a conqueſt, which is bound to no Law; but the will of the Conquerour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As theſe lead your friend (as you ſuppoſe) whither you would have him led: ſo they would have alſo led <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in their reſpective junctures of time, to <hi>Cuſhan-Ruſhathim,</hi> to <hi>Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> to <hi>Jabin,</hi> to the Princes &amp; chief powers of <hi>Midian,</hi> to <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Moab</hi> and the <hi>Philiſtines. Iſrael</hi> had been thus bound to ſo many ſucceſſive, and oppoſite Engagements: and bound up in bondage from ſeeking deliverance. No endeavour muſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be improved for any recovery of loſt right, if this doctrine (in favour of all that are in poſſeſſion and backed with power) ſhall take place. All whoſoever they be, in caſe they can get in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Soveraignty, may keep in: and all muſt aſſiſt in their hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, none may attempt any way, or make any plea for the moſt juſt recovery of their rights and liberties, ſo that either <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> ſinned as oft as they were delivered, or elſe theſe dictates of ſenſe, reaſon and conſcience, going this way which you point out, may lead your friend into miſtakes, and involve him in fears. Your diſtinction of adminiſtrations by vertue of a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract</hi> which makes a Law, or by vertue of a <hi>conqueſt</hi> which is bound to no Law, but to the will of the conquerour, were worth obſervation; if you would acquaint us which way the preſent power doth claim, for contract we know none, when we make any, both they and we ought to be faithful in it; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt (I think) you will not ſay, ſo you leave them to their own wills without any other rule in Government; in which you are ſcarce like to pleaſe any party, either thoſe in power or ſuch as are in ſubjection.</p>
            <p>As for the ſeveral queries, which you there put to your friend, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> I leave to your ſelf to finde out (which you can ſoon do) where the queſtion is miſerably begged, and that taken for granted;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:165758:10"/>which men of your friends ſcrupuloſities have never yielded, and in all that I have ſeen, (in the arguments of thoſe that ſtand up in defence of preſent proceedings) I do not finde ſo much as an attempt for the proof of it.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond branch of your friends doubt, you ſay, that <hi>the Engagement being a duty juſt to be required by the preſent pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers from their Subjects,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> 
               <hi>without the performance of which there is no protection due unto them, and neceſſary to be performed by all that will not profeſs themſelves deſirous to overthrow the preſent ſafety, and publick welfa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>re of the Nation; it cannot make thoſe that take it acceſſory to the guilt of thoſe that tender it, if any be in them, becauſe, &amp;c.</hi> But if the Engagement be not a duty, as men affected to the common cauſe of liberty (by your own conceſſions) are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, then guilt will follow upon ſuch ſuppoſition which you have laid down, and here you are very high in paſſing ſentence upon thoſe that (being conſcious to themſelves of the bonds of former Engagements) have forborn to ſubſcribe in this; <hi>that they deſerve not to have a being in the Common-wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which how prudertial it were to proceed in ſo high a way, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> I truſt thoſe that are in preſent power (how far ſoever by ſome forward ſpirits put on) will ſeriouſly conſider. What extreams are apt to beget, we have had ſad experience; ſuch wayes have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tended to the unjoynting, and ſeldom have contributed any thing to the ſettling of a Nation, and how equal I would have you more deliberately to ponder. You have obſerved, that the late Kings obligations and his Subjects were mutual; he was bound by Oath, as well as they, here ſubjects are called to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage without any Engagement at all from them in place of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign power, when we are as Subjects tyed, they are free, as Soveraigns; and what example can you finde, when a power is new fet up, to bring in a people for conſent under ſo high a penalty; In Scripture we cannot finde any other conſent in ſuch caſe then voluntary. And in the Conqueſt of this Nation (and other revolutions of State) we finde capitulations upon terms from either party; To preſs upon a people as ſoon as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a new power, not onely a Command over their Perſons and eſtates, (which already are in their hands) but alſo their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, is a practice I believe ſcarce to be paralelled. and having
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:165758:10"/>their perſons, and purſes in their power, they have cauſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect them, though as yet Subjects deſire to ſtand free in their Conſciences, protection ſhould be as large as ſubjection, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Eſtates are already ſubject, and theſe ought to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected for ſubjections ſake.</p>
            <p>Here you tell us <hi>of the end of the Engagement,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> 
               <hi>which is to give the Supreme power an aſſurance that we ſhall not betray it; but that we are willing to maintaine all good intelligence for publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments with it, notwithſtanding the preſent changes brought upon the Common-wealth.</hi> But this gloſs of yours, put upon the Engag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment utterly ſpoils all aſſurance that poſſibly can be given, either to this State or any other, as formerly hath been ſhewed, and I wiſh that you would more ſeriouſly conſider, for if no reſpect is to be had to outward forms, but to the intrinſecal good of the Common-wealth only; then all are at liberty (notwithſtanding ſuch Engagement) where they will to hold intelligence, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that their judgements tell them, that the publick is beſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for, that way in which they keep correſpondence; if for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Oaths of Allegiance, Supremacy, the Proteſtation and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant bound not at all to Monarchy there expreſſed; but to the publick good abſtracted from all particular forms, ſo that our Conſciences are ſtill free to ſubſcribe to any platform, then entring this Engagement it doth no more bind to a Republick or Democratie, but leaves us free for Monarchy, as formerly ſettled and eſtabliſhed; and I pray you farther take into your thoughts, which way the publick (as now it ſtands) by ſuch proceedings can reap advantage, Non-ſubſcibers (held back by conſcience dictates) are moſt unlike to be forward; for their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger being ſo cautelous before they engage with their pen, they will be equally wary how they engage with their ſword: ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves ſo tender of their own inward private peace; they will not be haſty to infeſt the publick; and as they have ſo they will ſtill in their place, and to their power withſtand de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of Tyranny, taking care that Monarchy (if ever again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhed) be kept within its bounds and limits; for thoſe whoſe hands are gained, I do not underſtand what ſecurity can be expected by it, hearts and hands (we know) do not alwayes hold pace together; and if any have minds bent to the publick,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165758:11"/>this is a good lurking-hole to hide them from ſuſpition, and thoſe interpretations of the Engagement which are held out to ſerve them in, together with others, wherewith many ſubſcribers (as I hear) ſatisfie themſelves, will alſo ſerve for an expedient to help them out, rendring their Conſciences innocent in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging, and freeing them from all Obligation of Conſcience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus engaged.</p>
            <p>Your third part (tending to ſatisfie your friends ſcruple, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> that <hi>the conſequence of the Engagement ſeems to tend to an oppoſition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the lawful Heir of the Crown, and right conſtitutions of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi>) preſuppoſed him to ſtand ſatisfied in the two former, and being built upon that bottome in caſe of diſ-ſatisfaction in thoſe; all this neceſſarily falls to the ground, and nothing needs to be ſpoken, that paſſage in it ſeems moſt obſervable, <hi>as for the diſſolution of your tye and obligation to the heir of the Crown, I ſhall refer you to look upon God, whether he hath not diſpoſſeſſed him wholly by his own doings and Councells, and by the guilt derived from his father and mother upon him, of all his intereſt in this Kingdom and Commonwealth; for becauſe his aim and the aim of thoſe that are about him, is not for the Common-wealth, but for the Kingdom, that is, not for the good of the ſociety, but for ſelf-greatneſs; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God who takes and gives the rights of Government, hath done as it ſeemeth good in his own eyes, both with him who according to men claims the Crown, and with them that were the ſupporters thereof, &amp;c.</hi> All of which (with much more that you have to the ſame purpoſe) might be ſatisfactory, if the <hi>work</hi> of God and not his <hi>word</hi> were our rule, if we muſt obſerve his <hi>hand,</hi> to go as he acts, and not his <hi>Command,</hi> to act what he enjoyns, God may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs him and any Monarchy on earth at pleaſure; Such is his Prerogative royal over all: but to infer from thence, that we may therefore engage againſt him (contrary to Covenant &amp; higheſt obligation of oath) is that which will at no hand fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. A good child ſeeks his fathers life, at that time when God is upon removal of him by ſtroke of death: Arguments of this ſtamp will give us warranty to act in all the evil that can be act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the State, or againſt it; all evil of this nature (penal, not oriminal) God does and owns, if we follow his hand we ſhall have ours as high in guilt, as his is in juſtice; theſe providences
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:165758:11"/>(which men in theſe times make their encour agements) are no other then temptations, and ſet a dore wide open to ſins of all ſorts, when they may be done with immunity and impunity of this divinity, will hold <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſpoilers are injuriouſly by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets branded as robbers, <hi>when God gave</hi> Iſrael <hi>to them, becauſe they had ſinned againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You further ſay, that you conceive, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> that <hi>the Prophecy of the Prophet Iſaiah, Chapter</hi> 24. <hi>verſe</hi> 21. <hi>is begun to be fulfilled amongſt us, ſomewhat more remarkably then in other parts of the earth as yet, which is this, And it ſhall come to paſs in that day, that the Lord ſhall puniſh the hoaſt of the high ones that are on high, and the Kings of the earth upon the earth, and they ſhall be gathered together as priſoners are gathered in the pit, and ſhall be ſhut up in priſon, and after many days ſhall be viſited; Then the Moon ſhall be confounded, and the Sun ſhall be aſhamed when the Lord of Hoaſts ſhall reign in Mount Sion, and before his ancients gloriouſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How far God will go on in this way, (on which you ſuppoſe he is entered) it is not ſafe for man to determine, only we know, that when he is doing his work, we muſt hold to our duty, and ſeeing there is a time when theſe thus threatned ſhall be viſited, (as there is foretold) not in judgement, but mercy (as appears in the context, and is confirmed by the conſent of interpreters) it ſhould be our work in the way and manner of the people of God of old, (acknowledging divine juſtice and their guilt) to implore the throne of grace in their behalf, that as in preſent they ſuffer what was threatned: ſo they may be fitted for the mercy promiſed. In the mean ſpace Propheſies are no rule for our actions but Precepts, not that which God ſays he will do, but what his will is that we ſhould do, muſt guide us; There was a Prophecy, that the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> ſhould be cut off, and the time laid down, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.26. there ſin was yet nothing leſſe that cut him off, he was delivered by the determinate Councel of God; there were ſtore of Prophecies, that witneſſed the ſuffering of Chriſt, and yet with wicked hands he was Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cified and ſlain, they fulfilled the Prophets in Condemning him.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:165758:12"/>
               <hi>David</hi> knew well that he muſt ſucceed <hi>Saul</hi> in the Kingdom, yet he waited Gods time and would have no hand in his remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, though providence was more then once urged as an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for his encouragement, <hi>that God had delivered him into his hands;</hi> if <hi>David</hi> had followed this rule, <hi>Saul</hi> had then dyed, and he over-timely (before Gods approved time) had intruded upon the Throne. After ſome plain language ſpoken to thoſe in power (which I wiſh may take that Prophets may have their mouths open, and with allowance to ſpeak, not <hi>Placentia,</hi> but <hi>Salubria</hi>) you give us your <hi>Item</hi> or admonition that <hi>we be not willfully ſcrupulous in theſe matters.</hi> In which you yet acquit your friend, when you ſpare not to charge divers others, where I wiſh you would take into your more ſerious conſideration, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> if the Engagement be lawful, and a reconciliation poſſible with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Oaths (by multiplication of diſtinctions and new rules for their obligation) whether yet all things are ſo clear and doubts ſo fully removed, that no cauſe at all of Scruple remains. If there were no other thing then the multitude of all degrees that reſt unſatisfied, (in whom both parts and piety are ſeen) that alone might be a good inducement, ſo far to ſuſpect your ſelf, that if not truth, yet evidence on your part is wanting, though I doubt not but in ſome caſes men may act againſt ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, when the judgement on the other part ſtands convinced, and the ſcruples appear reaſonleſs, or with very little of reaſon in them; yet to act againſt the dictates of their judgement (as many in this caſe muſt, whoſe reaſon on the moſt impartial en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the ſtate of the queſtion, determins yours in the nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive) were to ſin againſt conſcience, and to draw guilt upon their ſouls. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> You are pleaſed in your diſcourſe (as alſo ſeveral others) to tell us of the danger of reſiſting powers, which you ſay, holds of all in power, uſurped powers as well as others, when you might finde in approved Authors, ſuch diſtinctions of reſiſtance, as may acquit thoſe whom you ſeem to involve in ſo high a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, and render them innocent; and I pray you conſider in your ſelf, whether a juſt power with right unqueſtionable under a ſuppoſed forfeiture, may not challenge as much obſervance and ſubjection, and conſequently their reſiſtance to theſe, as danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as to men in power without title, onely by uſurpation.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:165758:12"/>That which in concluſion I beg is, that thoſe that ſee not with your eyes, and cannot warrant all that you approve, (having what to ſay if called unto it) may obtain from you a more favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable &amp; candid cenſure, then to be judged unworthy <hi>of a being in that Common-wealth</hi> where by right of birth they have their freedom, and that you would not think that ſelf-intereſt ſwayes ſo many to keep cloſe to the dictates of their Conſcience, in a way in all appearance to their preſent and private ruine; more of Chriſtianity would appear, in affording them your pitty and y our prayers, And the Lord give us a right judgement in all things.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="treatise">
            <head>The Second Treatiſe. Mr. <hi>Dureus</hi> his friend further ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, Or, A Reply to ſome Objections made againſt his Conſiderations concerning the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of taking the Engagement; affectionately offered to the ſerious conſideration of thoſe that are ſcrupled at it. or at his Conſiderations about it.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Shall freely confeſs, that the Scope of your papers, (put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my hands a few dayes ago) is to me very acceptable; for which cauſe, as I think my ſelf obliged, ſo in all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs I ſhall endeavour your further ſatisfaction; that ſo farre as the Lord ſhall inable me to diſcerne the truth, I may hold it forth, for the manifeſtation of our duty in the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of the Engagement.<note place="margin">The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</note> And if a courſe of amicable conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces had been more freely taken up heretofore, and regularly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed upon this ſubject, amongſt godly Brethren, as it ought to have been in the Law of Peace and Truth; I make no doubt but ſome of theſe breaches might have been prevented, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſome of the old waſts and ruinous heaps, might alſo have been repaired: but becauſe theſe thoughts of healing and of building up, have not been laid to heart; therefore our unſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlements
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:165758:13"/>have not onely continued: but we have therein been led on, unto ſad courſes of new diviſions, and unchriſtian animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities; as for my ſelf, I can call the ſearcher of all hearts to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that I have none other aim but to diſcharge a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in this buſineſs, and for the Goſpels ſake to ſeek out a Goſpel-Remedy unto our publick evils; for hereunto my thoughts have been many years ago lead forth; and ſeeing my affections do ſtill continue to proſecute this deſign, not with humane contrivements, but by the Grace of God in true ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city; I may therefore hope that God may be pleaſed in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing happily to make me inſtrumental to his glory, and my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial ſollicitations for the wayes of Unity and Peace, may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come effectual to the comfort of his children: however I ſhall not ceaſe to concur in true humility with prayers, and ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons unto the Father of Lights, and the fountain of all good gifts, that in end all who are upright in heart, may according to his Counſel be united in the ſpirit of Chriſt, and thereby (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſome diverſities of apprehenſions about humane affairs) be fitted more and more in ſpiritual concernments for his ſervice, and their mutual edification: beſeeching him withall, that none of our weakneſſes and ſinful diſtances of ſpirit amongſt our ſelves, may bring any reproach upon the holy profeſſion of the Goſpel, and of our Miniſtery; or open the mouthes of our adverſaries, to take advantages againſt us while they watch for our haltings. It is a ſad matter that the Engagement intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for a ground of mutual ſafety, and an aſſurance of harmleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and indempnity amongſt thoſe that truly intend the intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecal good of the Common wealth, ſhould be ſo far miſ-under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, as to prove rather an object of ſtrife and diviſion then of an agreement;<note place="margin">The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</note> and I am ſorry that any of my expreſſions wherein I meant not to cenſure any body, who is conſcionable, week or well-meaning; ſhould be taken in another ſenſe then I did offer them; but whether I have been in the fault by utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them unadviſedly, or others, who through prejudices have miſtaken me, I hope upon a further diſquiry of theſe matters, it will in due time ſufficiently appear, nor ſhall I ever (God willing) be found averſe from rectifying a fault if I can diſcern it, when it is laid open to me.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:165758:13"/>
            <p>I ſhall then come to the obſervations which you offer upon my conſiderations of the Engagement, and that we may with more brevity, clearenesſs, and readineſs, have recourſe to the heads of matters whereof notice is to be taken; I ſuppoſe our beſt courſe will be to mark the ſame with numericall Figures in the margen of our Papers, which ſhall ſhew the things which anſwer each other, and direct us to the places to which we ſpeak,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt thing you take notice of, is; that yeilding an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to be ſettled between a King and his Subjects by a Law. according to which he is to be their King, and they his Subjects; yet you ſay I produce no ſuch Law in this caſe:<note place="margin">The plea that the King cannot be counted a tranſgreſſor of the law.</note> and if either the Law cannot be produced upon the tranſgreſſion of which he doth <hi>ipſo facto</hi> forfeit his Regalities: or if his tranſgreſſion of that Law cannot bee proved; that then in this caſe there is no ground to quiet mens minds concerning that which is befallen him. Now that a Law in this caſe cannot be produced you aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert upon Mr. <hi>Cooke</hi> authority, who gives the reaſon why no ſuch Law was made, to be the ſame for which <hi>Solon</hi> made none to puniſh <hi>Parrioides,</hi> and that he cannot be counted a tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of the Laws, you aſſert upon this ground; becauſe Kings in this Nation act nothing as Kings in their own perſons, but only by ſubordinate Agents: whence you conclude, that neither ſuch a Law being extant, nor although it were extant, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a capacity of being a tranſgreſs or againſt it; the thing which I alleage for diſsabling the obligation of his Subjects from him, can be of no force.</p>
            <p>To this I ſhall give this anſwer.</p>
            <p>That in my diſcourſe I did not ſuppoſe any particular Poſitive and expreſſe Law extant between the King and his People ſpecifying the tenure of their mutual obligation,<note place="margin">The anſwer doth ſhew what the law is to which a King is bound.</note> how far it ſhould bind or not bind the Subject to him; but I ſuppoſe only this much: that there is a natural tacite and implicite law extant, known and preſuppoſed by all men who make any contracts one with another, which is this: that no contract doth other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe bind but according to the condition upon which it is made. If then a King is a King only upon this condition, that he ſhall intend to Rule legally, and not by will and force. and if
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:165758:14"/>he breake this condition and actually attempt to rule, not le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally, but by will and force, then he hath <hi>ipſo facto</hi> forfeited his Regality: nor was it needfull that any penalty ſhould be expreſly denounced againſt any ſuch tranſgreſſion no more then in <hi>Solons</hi> Common-wealth againſt <hi>Parrieides,</hi> not becauſe ſuch a fault (if committed) was not puniſhable, but becauſe all men by nature know what puniſhment it may deſerve. So then the want of a poſitive law in this matter doth not make that which I ſay at all invalid: for although it be granted that there is no particular law declaring this or that act of his, to be a full forfeiture of truſt: yet this is a known law to all, that conſider him to be under an oath of Ruling legally; that in caſe he doth ſet himſelf to Rule lawleſſy, he hath broken his oath, and fully forfeited his truſt.</p>
            <p>I ſay then that although in my diſcourſe I named no law, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> yet my meaning was to produce the law of nature when I ſaid that the <hi>Oaths were reciprocall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">What ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagance to Kings.</note> 
               <hi>ſtanding &amp; falling together,</hi> for this I take to be the law of nature in this caſe: that if a King doth break the oath of his legality towards his Subjects, his Subjects are abſolved from the oath of their allegiance towards him.</p>
            <p>Concerning that which you ſay, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that Kings as Kings act nothing in their own perſons,<note place="margin">What laws Kings are exempted from, &amp; not counted tranſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greſſors of in their owne perſons, and upon what conditions that exempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion is granted them.</note> but only by their ſubordinat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents who alone are puniſhable when the law is tranſgreſsed, I know that this is the law in Caſes of particular concernement, wherein ſome ſpeciall poſitive laws are tranſgreſsed, but of the generall concernement. whereby the whole ground of all le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal governement is taken away, that law cannot be underſtood. Beſides I conceive, that the poſitive law which you mention, doth ſuppoſe that the King is oliged to give up his ſubordinate Agents (the tranſgeſsors of the laws) unto the courſe of Juſtice, and not to take all their faults upon himſelf, ſo as to protect them with the ſhield of his indemnity, or with the force of his word againſt the execution of vindicative Juſtice: for if he doth this; then he puts himſelf as to his own perſon, out of the caſe of indemnity wherein the law puts it: nor can that law be counted valid for him againſt his own will, and againſt the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the law of nature; which in this eaſe doth make him
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:165758:14"/>guilty, for if a King as a King, by the intent of the law, doth act nothing in his owne perſon but by his agents; and yet he will not be counted to have acted by his agents but to have done all their faults in his own perſon, then he declares <hi>ipſo facto</hi> that he will not have the intent of the law valid as to himſelf, but that he will ſtand in his agents roome and be look't upon as in their perſon and under their guilt, and conſequently not as a King but as a tranſgreſsor; <hi>non quod volenti non fit injuria, eſt regula juris.</hi> Therefore I conceive thus;<note place="margin">By <hi>3.</hi> wayes the preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption from being a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor may be loſt by Kings.</note> That a King may make void as to himſelf, and looſe the prerogative of the law made in favour to his perſon three ways. 1. If he ſet himſelf directly to diſanul the general ground of all laws. For this cannot be imputed to any ſubordinat agents as their guilt, for they are lookt upon and made puniſhable only as tranſgreſsors in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular matters. 2. If he doth in oppoſition to the intent of the law made for puniſhing tranſgreſsors, and for exempting his own perſon from the guilt of particular tranſgreſſions; take up on himſelf all the guilt of particular faults to protect iniquity and illegality; then he doth effectually make void the prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative which the law doth give him. 3. If he doth by force take upon him to hinder the execution of the ſentence of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Judicature, for the protecting of tranſgreſſors againſt the law; for to do this; is the higheſt act of illegal government, and in effect the putting down of all laws. In all which Caſes if you can make it appear to me rationally that by your poſitive law the King is to be meant no tranſgreſsor; I ſhall confeſs a miſtake, but till then give me leave to think that I am no ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to Reaſon, when I am bold to ſay, that no poſitive law of any Nation in the world, can diſanul the law of Nature, which in ſuch-like caſes, doth preſent a King even as a King to be in his own perſon a tranſgreſsor to the law-making power of the Nation, which is to be governed legally and not arbitrarily.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing which you take notice of, is a ſeeming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtency between two paſſages of my diſcourſe. In the one (you think) I Judge definitly in the higheſt way of the Rights which Supream powers have over us, and in the other which is pag. 10. I declare that it doth not belong to me or to any privat man to Judge definitively of the rights which the Supre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:165758:15"/>powers in this world pretend to have to their places.</p>
            <p>To reconcile this ſeeming inconſiſtency, I ſhall deſire you to reflect upon two things,<note place="margin">The anſwer doth ſhew the grounds of reconcileing it.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> The direct intent and proper ſubject of each part of my diſcourſe, whereunto the things ſeemingly inconſiſtent do relate; which things in both places being very much different, and bringing a different reſpect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the paſſages ſuppoſed to be oppoſite, when you ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſame, I hope your miſtake will be rectified.</p>
            <p>For in the firſt place my purpoſe is to declare what the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental conſtitution of the Government of this State is, as I conceive it agreeable to the Univerſal law of nature; by which all free Common-wealths are ſettled within themſelves. But in the ſecond place <hi>viz.</hi> pag. 10. my purpoſe is to declare how my friend ought to behave himſelf for the quieting of his ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Conſcience in the doubts which he had concerning the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular preſent Powers, and the lawfulnes of their coming to their places.</p>
            <p>The proper ſubject of my diſcourſe in the firſt place, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Legiſlative power of all Nations, as they are Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, and how in this Nation that power hath been ſettled of old: and the proper ſubject whereof I ſpeak in the ſecond place, is concerning the particular ways by which the preſent powers are come, and have a right to their places, which are things of a very different nature.</p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt, if you look upon the Univerſal law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I ſuppoſe you wil grant that no man ought to be ignorant of it;<note place="margin">The applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the grounds to ſhew the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilement of the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</note> &amp; if you look upon the conſtitution of this State, as that law is obſerved therein, I hope you will alow me as one in matriculat into the Common-wealth, and concerned as well as others in the common welfare thereof, the judgement of diſcretion to conſider and declare what I obſerve therein: which at this time I think is my duty to mention, but concerneing the ſecond, I give advice to my friend how he may quiet his ſpirit about the matters which concern him not, and whereat he ſeemes to be troubled, and decline to make my ſelfe a definitive Judge of the particular rights and proceedings of thoſe that God hath ſet over us to Rule the Common-wealth. So then in the forme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I obſerve what the law is under which we live: and in the latter
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:165758:15"/>I refrain from the judicature of particular matters whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to I have no calling to be a Iudge:<note place="margin">A miſtake concerning the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons right to make laws objected.</note> and what inconſiſtency is between theſe purpoſes, and between the diſcourſes, which to this effect I make upon theſe ſubjects; I ſhall refer now to your ſecond thoughts to collect, wherein I hope your imaginary difficultie to reconcile theſe paſſages will eaſily vaniſh,</p>
            <p>Concerning that which I ſay of the Cuſtome of this Nation, that the Commons at all times have uſed to aske and propoſe the making of Laws, &amp; that the Lords &amp; King were wont to give their conſent thereunto, you ſay, <hi>I do as far in this miſtake as I did forget my ſelf in the other.</hi> To this I ſay, It is well if I am not further miſtaken. For I ſhall not ſtick to declare ingeniouſly the truth of my preſent thoughts, that when I now reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the expreſſions which there I have uſed,<note place="margin">The anſwer ſhews the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take and whence it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds.</note> concerning the National Cuſtom, and compare them with what you offer to be conſidered here (although I ſee my ſelf not guilty of the miſtake wherewith you charge me, but can diſcern the grounds of your miſtaking the drift and ſenſe of my words to have been ſomwhat of the Printers fault; ſomewhat of your own inadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of my meaning yet) my words ſeem to myſelf ſomewhat more full then they needed to have been for the end for which I uttered them. For my end was only to ſhew that the received Cuſtome and liberty, whereby the Commons are wont to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the making of laws, and the Lords and King are deſired to give their aſſent thereunto, did ariſe at firſt, and was ſince con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued upon the juſt and natural foundation of all laws in a free Nation: which is the reaſon of the Body thereof in Parliament. which I ſay hath the ſole right to propoſe and chuſe the laws by which the Nation is to be ruled. This drift of mine you do not obſerve, and the fault of the Printer hath helped your miſtake; for in the laſt Impreſſion which I conjecture you have made uſe of; the particle <hi>where</hi> is put in ſtead of <hi>whence</hi> which was in the firſt, intimating the dependance of the cuſtome of the Commons of this Nation upon the law of nature mentioned immediatly before. Now becauſe I intended to point at as much of this right and liberty of nature as I did find extant in the practiſe of our Parliament, and withall had a mind briefly to intimate the moſt material differences of Rights, which were in each of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:165758:16"/>members of Parliament, with reference to the whole Body, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fore-named law of nature; therefore I perceive my expreſſions did run out, under the generall terme of a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Cuſtome, aſwel upon that which by right might be practiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: or rather by the nature of this conſtitution of government is proper to be practiſed, as upon that which <hi>de facto</hi> was in uſe amongſt us.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant that the laws have had their riſe ſometimes from the one,<note place="margin">How the Laws do riſe from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and how from the King and Lords deffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently</note> ſometimes from the other houſe: but when I ſaid that it was (as I ſuppoſed) a perpetual cuſtome in this Nation for the Commons at all times to aske and propoſe the making of laws, I had an eye to the Coronation-oath, wherein the King is ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liged to ſwear that he ſhal maintain the laws <hi>quas vulgus elege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> which doth ſuppoſe to my underſtanding, no leſs then what I expreſs, <hi>viz.</hi> that the right of asking and propoſing of laws to be made doth originally reſide in the people; with a tacite obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation in the King to conſent thereunto. As antient then as the Coronation-oath is, ſo long I ſuppoſe the Commons do lay claime to this right of chuſing laws for themſelves, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though all this be granted, yet it doth not follow that the King and Lords might not alſo propoſe any thing at all, for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of laws unto the Commons. For to aſſert this right to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long originally and primarily to theſe, doth not wholly exclude the other from it: nor do my expreſſions import much more then a direct aſſertion of the right of the Commons which is in practiſe: which being raiſed and derived from the law of nature, might be inferred to be <hi>de jure</hi> primarily practiſed by them, and truly (though you ſeeme to deny it, yet) I have been told very credibly and circumſtantially, that the Commons ſince the ſitting of this Parliament, have more then once upon ſpecial immergencys declared at Conferences to the Lords that this was their right, as they were the repreſentatives of the Nation, and Truſtees for common ſafety. It is alſo granted that the Lords or King have by a received cuſtome freely given or refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their aſſent to Bills offered as they have ſeen cauſe: this ſheweth that they ſate not in Parliament as meere ſervants un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerned in the maine; but as joynt-Councellors for the main, in the things wherein their ſervice was to be made uſe of to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:165758:16"/>the State, a man may be in his Principal relation a ſervant to another, and yet in ſuch a degree of honour, as not to be obliged to do any thing by meere command without his owne free conſent: and ſo I conceive Kings and Lords to be in a free Nation, they may for themſelves (if they think not fit to act.) ſurceaſe, but they cannot pretend to a negative voice, ſo as to make it unlawful for thoſe that have a right to order their own affairs, to act without them, they are then to be counted <hi>Servi Honorarii non Mancipia legum,</hi> and becauſe they may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered juſtly as members of the State, who have a conſiderable State to venture in it, therefore they cannot be in equity de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of a conſultative vote in the making of laws (except by ſome faults they make themſelves incapable thereof) although the power of chuſing &amp; making them doth not primarily belong unto them but to the Commons alone: and to theſe a right and prerogative to ſee them kept and executed, for herewith the Repreſentees intruſt them.</p>
            <p>That which you obſerve concerning the oath of allegiance (that it was made in our age) is no ways inconſiſtent with my aſſertion, that by the conſent of all ages, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the oath of allegiance ought to be underſtood as I explain it:<note place="margin">In what ſenſe the Oath of alleagance hath been in all ages.</note> for if you obſerve the ſtrain of my diſcourſe, you will ſee that I ſpeake of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the oath as it is in the law of nature and Nations, that is, as in all ages ſuch Oaths have been uſed; for all promiſes of Fealty and of free ſubjection unto Kings and liege Lords, in all people and Nations governed rationally by laws, are in my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the ſame kind with our oath of allegiance: and therefore this particular oath made in our age upon a ſpecial e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergency, ought to be underſtood no otherwiſe then that ſame oath hath been always taken at all other times.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
            <p>The Comment which you ſay I make upon the third article of the Covenant, is your miſtake of my conſtruction of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,<note place="margin">Concerning the ſence of the third ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Covenant whether the promiſe to preſerve the King be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional yea, or no.</note> and not my miſtake of the meaning thereof, for I change not the <hi>In</hi> into <hi>If,</hi> as you ſay I do: for look upon my words again and you ſhall ſee that I aleadge the expreſſion as it is in the text of the Covenant, but yet I ſay that the <hi>In</hi> of the Covenant doth contain a limitation of the defence and preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion promiſed to the King and his Authority, for if we promiſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:165758:17"/>to defend him and his Authority onely in the defence and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Religion and Liberties, then we are neither bound unto him abſolutely, nor otherwiſe but in order to theſe, ſo then our meaning is to be bound, firſt to defend theſe for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and then him and his Authority are included therein. But now if it ſhould fall out that be by his own default ſhould not be found in theſe, if hee ſhould put himſelf out of the ſphere of that protecteion, which we oblige ourſelves to maintain towards Religion and Liberty: and if he will not be lookt upon as ſub ordinate thereunto, but regarded by us, meerly for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: is not then his ſhare of ſafety due to him this way (but refuſed by him as thus offered) leſt to him, as from our acts of protection, becauſe the intention of defending and preſerving him and his juſt Authority, is taken up and concluded onely as within the bounds of that endeavour, which is to be put forth for the maintaining of Religion and liberty, which is ſo far from being a forced and corſtrained ſenſe of the words that the more ſtrictly you cleave to the letter thereof, the leſſe reſpect is to be had unto him alone for himſelf, and without due regard to Religion and liberty. I do not ſay (as you miſconſture me) that the words of the Covenant are to be meant of the Kings preſervation of Religion &amp; liberty, but I underſtand them of our preſervation thereof, and I grant that with it we are bound to intend his preſervation alſo, yet always ſo, as to intend him and his intereſt within that of religion and liberty and not without it, or ſeparate from it, and by itſelf: nor did I leave out the words immediately following <hi>that the world may bear witueſs with our Conſciences of our loyalty, and that we have no thoughts to dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his Majeſties juſt power and greatneſs</hi>) upon any ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign as you immagine at all: for they do take nothing from the ſenſe of a limited protection which I urge, but rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the ſame, by declaring that to include all the reſpect which we owe to him within our preſervation of Religion and Liberty is the conſcionable tenure of our true loyalty, and that we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs before all the world, that we acknowledge it not due to him upon any other termes, and that in ſo doing we foment no purpoſe to diminiſh any thing of his juſt power and greatneſs becauſe it cannot be imagined that ever any power or greatneſ
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:165758:17"/>was legally intended to be given him, or juſtly poſſeſſed by him, which is not conſiſtent with the true Religion, and the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the <hi>Nations.</hi> Whereupon my inference concerning him, (which I perceive you miſinterpret, as if I offered it, as the meaning of the words of the <hi>Covenant</hi>) doth follow, that if he would not concur with the Repreſentatives towards the maintaining of their Religion and Liberties, he put himſelf out of the protection, which in order thereunto was intended to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him.</p>
            <p>Here by the way obſerve a fault in the printing of the <hi>Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations;</hi> for whereas it is ſaid, <hi>none but his ſubjects are bound to defend his perſon,</hi> it ſhould be <hi>none of his Subjects are bound, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay then upon the whole matter with you, that the things charged againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> wherein they were accuſed to have an evil eye againſt the King were falſly and injuriouſly charged upon it, and juſtly diſavowed by the <hi>Proteſtations</hi> which the <hi>Parliament</hi> put forth; becauſe it was not poſſible for the <hi>Parliament</hi> to look any better way upon the <hi>King,</hi> then through the proſpect of Religion and Liberty; and if he did vaniſh out of their ſight, whiles they did heartily ſeek him within that proſpect; it muſt not be imputed to the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> eye, but unto his own carriage and motions which made him inviſible to them there, where they were bound to ſeek him, and he bound to be found.</p>
            <p>Touching the cauſes why the <hi>King</hi> was laid aſide, you ſay, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> that I ſeem unreſolved whether it was guilt in his Majeſty, or jealouſie in the Houſes that occaſioned the Votes of Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>addreſſes. You ſay well, that I ſeem unreſolved,<note place="margin">Concerning the Votes of Nonaddreſſes whether they came from guilt in the King, or jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie in the Houſes.</note> becauſe I was reſolved, not to ſeem a reſolver of that buſineſs. For I think it contrary to the Rule of my place and Calling, to make my ſelf a Judge of the matter between them.</p>
            <p>The Reaſons why a private man ought not to judge defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively of the proceedings of his Superiours in their places, you will do well in matters of this nature, to follow as you ſee I do. And if all our Brethren would do ſo, they would free their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits from great Snares, and find a readier way to do their duty without murmuring, then now they can light upon.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:165758:18"/>
            <p>But touching the parallel which you make between the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> and a man jealous of his Wife, out of <hi>Numb.</hi> 5. methinks the <hi>Text</hi> will not yield the concluſion which you ſeem to infer from it;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 24.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.3.</note> for it is clear, that <hi>Moſes</hi> permitted the <hi>Jews</hi> to give their Wives a Bill of divorce for ſlight occaſions of diſlike taken up againſt them, although they were altogether guiltleſs: therefore the intent of the Law of jealouſie in <hi>Numb.</hi> 5. ſeems not to be for ordering of the way of her diſmiſſion; for a Bill of Divorce did order that way but only to quiet the ſpirit of jealouſie, in the Husband, by bringing the matter between him and his Wife to ſome iſſue by Gods determination of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of doubt.</p>
            <p>I know not why you ſay, that I ſeem to judge it not unreaſonable, that the people may caſt off their Kings <hi>ad placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi> It is altogether againſt my judgment; for except there be a breach of the fundamental truſt, I know no <hi>placitum</hi> to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable; for there ought to be no more a divorce between the <hi>King</hi> and his People; for every ſlight cauſe, then between a Man and his Wife; and I think you intend not to make the bond ſtronger between a King and his People, then God hath made it between a Wife and her Husband. If then you will aſſert that there ought to be no divorce between them, without a breach of the fundamental Relation, which may be called <hi>State-Adultery,</hi> I ſhall not contradict you; but if you will go beyond the judgment of diſcretion peremptorily to define, where and what the firſt breach of truſt was, I am not allowed to follow you, yet without any determinate judicature to look diſcreetly upon theſe matters, and to contemplate what may be rational<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid unto them; I ſhall not blame you for it, <hi>viz.</hi> to conſider whether the <hi>King</hi> made not a fundamental breach from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> when he intended to diſſolve it by a <hi>Declaration,</hi> wherein he condemned them (if I am not miſtaken) to be Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Rebels? and whether when he called another <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> he did not actually as it were marry himſelf to another Wife?</p>
            <p>Concerning the Votes of Non-addreſſes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> you ſay <hi>they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called, and the King was made thereby an Object of the Oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay it is true, the Votes were recalled, but yet the repeal
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:165758:18"/>was only in order to a Treaty: therefore after the Treaty,<note place="margin">In what ſence the Votes of Non-addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called.</note> if no full concluſion did enſue, he was to be <hi>in ſtatu que prius.</hi> The repeal then was not abſolute, as the prohibition of addreſſes was: if therefore the Votes of abſolute Non-addreſſes did diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the obligation as to private perſons: and the Votes of conditional addreſſes for a publick Treaty did not reſtore it in the event, I ſee not how he could become an object of our al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance by repealing of thoſe Votes.</p>
            <p>That which you ſay againſt the reaſons which I alledge to ſhew, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
               <hi>that the Engagement is ſo far from being oppoſite to the Oath of Allegiance, and the National Covenant, that it may rather be a confirmation of the ground for which both the one and the other was binding;</hi> runs out upon a great miſconſtruction of my ſence, which eaſily might have been otherwiſe underſtood; for it was very obvious for any body to imagine, that in this caſe when we ſpeak of a <hi>Common wealth,</hi> a <hi>Chriſtian Common-wealth</hi> is to be underſtood; and upon this preſuppoſal,<note place="margin">What are the eſſentials of a Chriſtian Common-wealth.</note> which I thought no ways obſcure, I ſaid, <hi>to be governed by Laws, to have the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and the National Freedom, are things abſolutely neceſſary and eſſential to the being of a Common-wealth, meaning a Chriſtian Common-wealth,</hi> and although actually there be few, or have been few ſuch <hi>Common-wealths</hi> in the world; yet that doth not refute my aſſertion of the nature of the thing; but that which you add concerning our Oaths that they had a reſpect not only to the <hi>eſſe,</hi> but alſo to the <hi>bene eſſe</hi> of the Nation doth ſeem ſome what more material: yet you miſtake me wholly,<note place="margin">How Oaths concerning means to an end are bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> when you ſay that I take for granted, that all our Oaths did barely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the <hi>eſſe</hi> not the <hi>bene eſſe,</hi> or external adminiſtration of the Nation; for I grant that we ſwore not only to the remote end, but alſo to the means which had a direct tendency thereunto, which then was judged by the reaſon of the Nation to be the form of <hi>Government,</hi> which at that time was eſtabliſhed: this I freely grant, but withall I conceive, that the intent of all ſuch Oaths was only to oblige unto the means ſo long, ſo far, and <hi>in quantum</hi> as they ſhould have a direct tendency to the main end for which they were taken; and not abſolutely whether they ſhould have a tendency to the main end or no, whence this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence will follow, that if the means ceaſe to have ſuch a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, (which upon emergencies may fall out) or become de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:165758:19"/>to the end for which they were choſen, then the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to uſe them for ſuch an end (though ſetled by an Oath) is no more binding; for if the Oath did bind only as to means for an end, and the things ſworn to, do ceaſe to be what they were, <hi>viz.</hi> means to that end: then to my underſtanding there is no further obligation in that Oath towards the uſe of them; and I pray conſult your Caſuiſts upon this matter, whether they can ſhew any reaſon to contradict this aſſertion. Now this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to me a clear truth in reſpect of the obligation in general, of an Oath to the uſe of any means whatſoever, I ſhall proceed to ſtate the caſe ſomewhat nearer to our preſent condition, as I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, and made it the ground of my diſcourſe. I conceive then,<note place="margin">The Caſe of taking the National Oaths, and the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſtated.</note> that private men in publick concernments touching the Government of the State; when there is a neceſſary change in it, and a queſtion, whether this or that form is moſt conducible to the main end of common ſafety? and whether the means formerly ſetled towards that end have any further fitneſs and tendency thereunto, yea or no? I ſay, in this matter of delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and in all concernments of ſuch a publick nature; private men are to be determined by the judgment of the ſupream pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which is over them, for the time: if then I (being a private man) be at one time called upon to declare my faithfulneſs to the uſe of the means which my Superiours judge fitteſt for publick ſafety, do oblige my ſelf under them to be faithful thereunto: and at another time, be called upon again, to declare my faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to the uſe of other means (emergencies in the judgement of the ſupream powers, having changed the nature of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer) or to declare my conſtant reſolution, to be faithful to the main end of common peace and ſafety, notwithſtanding the changes which they think neceſſary to make in the means; if I ſay, I be thus called upon, as one to be determined in ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, by the ſupreme powers that are over me, do act without ſcrupling that which in it ſelf I think juſt and lawful in my place to do; what blame can I bear, for yielding to different <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations</hi> at ſeveral times, and upon different and neceſſary emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies? now if this be the caſe whereof I ſpeak, and whereinto we are caſt (as clearly it is) then your whole diſcourſe <hi>concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the intention of a ſwearer towards the end, in contradiction to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:165758:19"/>the means expreſſed in his Oath,</hi> is to no purpoſe, and I have cauſe to wonder that you exſpaciat ſo largely upon a ſubject whereof there is ſo little occaſion and appearance of ground given from that which I ſay; for I ſay nothing but that the ſence of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement</hi> to my underſtanding doth confirm the ground and main end for which the former Oaths were taken. I ſpeak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of any mans private intentions; or of the interpretations which he may make mentally of the Oaths which are put to him, though different from the ſence of thoſe that offer them: I am ſo far from allowing of this in any body, that I conceive all ſuch practices to be a mocking of God and men; but I ſpeak clearly of the proper intent of the <hi>Engagement,</hi> and how conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent the ſenſe thereof is with the main end of the former Oaths. And as for that which the former Oaths did mention touching the forms of <hi>Government</hi> then in being; I ſay that I conceive none of them ſo eſſential to any <hi>Nation,</hi> as that upon exigent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities they may not be altered by the ſupreme power of that <hi>Nation:</hi> and how you come to conceive that I think it not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable for a People to caſt off their <hi>Kings,</hi> or change the forme of their <hi>Government</hi> meerly <hi>ad placitum,</hi> when as I ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly limit thoſe alterations to a neceſſary exigency; I would have ſome cauſe to wonder, if I knew not that it is very incident to men foreſtalled in judgement or affection againſt others, to be inclined to miſ underſtand their words, and upon imaginary advantages againſt the opinions fathered upon them, to be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to triumph over fictitious abſurdities. I ſhall therefore paſſe by your whole diſcourſe concerning the caſe of one coming to a <hi>Garriſon;</hi> Concerning the <hi>Canan-Oath</hi> to confirm the <hi>Prelacy.</hi> Concerning the ſecond <hi>Article</hi> of the <hi>National-Covenant,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the making void of all ſecurity in every <hi>Oath</hi> which the <hi>State</hi> may preſcribe, Concerning <hi>Zedekiah</hi> and how he might have juſtified his perjury againſt <hi>Nebucadnezer,</hi> Concerning the <hi>Elders</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that they might have broken their Oath to the <hi>Gibeonites.</hi> Concerning <hi>Saul,</hi> that he might have juſtified the wrong he did unto them, and concerning the benefit which the preſent <hi>State</hi> may reap by the <hi>Engagement</hi> upon ſuch an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation thereof as you are willing to put upon it, in my name againſt my ſence.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:165758:20"/>
            <p>I ſay, I ſhall paſs by all theſe particulars, becauſe they are to no purpoſe: the whole caſe and my ſence againſt which you pretend to alleage them, being wholly miſtaken, as I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhewed; nor came it ever in my heart to think that any mans private interpretation or intention to ſome remote end might juſtifie him to take any Oath in a ſence which is diſagreeing from the meaning of thoſe that give it; nor is it poſſible by any conſequence to infer any ſuch thing as juſtifiable, from any thing which I do ſay; and if you can make it appear that any ſuch thing doth truly follow upon any aſſertion of mine, I ſhall as willingly as you condemn it.</p>
            <p>My Friends objection from the third Article of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> you intend to ſtrengthen two ways againſt the <hi>Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, when I confeſs that the former intentions to preſerve the priviledges of Parliament as then they were ſetled, cannot now be proſecuted; you tell me, that this alone is enough to create a bigger ſcruple then there is force in my anſwer to wipe off.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, you make uſe of the plea which I alleage for the juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of my Friend, to condemn thoſe who did that which he could not allow, but rather found himſelf obliged to prevent and oppoſe in his place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the firſt if you had ſhewn what the ſcruple was, which that confeſſion might create, I could have ſpoken to it, but ſeeing you conceal it, it is not my work to conjecture what it may be: the rather, becauſe I cannot ſuſpect that you ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it to be a ſin, to lay down alterable intentions, when God makes them impoſſible or ſinful to be proſecuted.</p>
            <p>Touching the ſecond I do not allow of your inference, <hi>viz: That if my friend is excuſable from breach of Covenant in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringement of Parliament-Priviledges, becauſe he did contribute no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing thereunto: that therefore I do plainly charge with breach of Covenant thoſe who brought this change upon the ſtate.</hi> I ſay this conſequence doth not follow, becauſe the caſes of thoſe that brought this change about, was far different from that of my Friends; and ſuch as by their place might make that to be right in them, which in my Friend would have been wrong: here the ſaying is morally true, <hi>cum duo faciunt idem, non eſt idem.</hi> For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:165758:20"/>though they are engaged into the ſame <hi>Covenant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Whether they who were the Authours of the change of Government, are to be judged guilty of the breach of Covenant yea or no?</note> yet the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of publick and private perſons, or perſons in truſt or without truſt, makes a vaſt difference as to matters of publick concernment: nor am I a competent judge to define what is right or wrong in the management of publick places, whereof the nature and circumſtances are unknown to me, nor what the ſpecial emergencies of State were, which might juſtifie their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings: therefore I dare not beyond my line take upon me that which you do, to condemn them for <hi>Covenant-breakers,</hi> and that unheard: ſurely if in ſuch caſes every private man may make himſelf a Judge of the affairs intruſted unto others in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick places, all Government will be utterly diſſolved, and unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricable confuſions will enſue. The fatall neceſſity of a State may be ſeen and apprehended by ſome that ſit at the ſtern other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then by others:<note place="margin">Nay, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen that they are a minor party.</note> and how far a party of Rulers in number leſs, and yet in point of truſt more conſiderable, may act by their own apprehenſions of neceſſity, contrary to the ſence of a major party, is a thing which ſince the troubles of both Nations and the ſitting of this Parliament hath oft times been decided. If you look upon the proceedings of the leading men of both Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, who have ventured upon enterprizes of an extraordinary nature, in extraordinary emergencies, both without the aſſent, and ſometimes againſt the ſence of the major part. Now when men in ſupream truſt moſt conſiderable, differ in judgment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the way of common ſafety, from others who are in the ſame truſt, but leſs conſiderable: what can we who are ſtanders by, not acquainted with the grounds of their deliberations, nor called to the arbitrement of differences between them, do in ſuch a caſe either as <hi>Chriſtians</hi> or as rational men; but pray to God that they may agree,<note place="margin">How ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders-by that look upon publick de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Rulers in chief, ſhould behave the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and being peaceable in our own thoughts not to meddle beyond our line to judge either way, or to foment parties, or to provoke and harden one ſide againſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; but to perſwade all indifferently unto that concurrence and unity of ſpirit, which in known duties for common concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is out of all doubt moſt edifying and blameleſs. If you would joyn with me to follow the Rules of this Divinity, rather then give way to prejudicate imaginations, you would ſee juſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:165758:21"/>cauſe to ſuſpend your judgment concerning the plea which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have made of neceſſity, from cenſuring it in them as ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary and pretended: and if you had a mind to refute the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of any point of (as you call it) <hi>State-Divinity</hi> to break <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants,</hi> you would certainly be inabled to do it more effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and impartially then hitherto you have done any thing which I have met withall in theſe papers; for the reaſonings which <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the <hi>Elders</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (as you perſonate them) might have alledged, and which you think <hi>Saul</hi> took up to colour his breach of <hi>Covenant</hi> with the <hi>Gibeonites:</hi> although indeed as you ſay, ſuch reaſonings come from unbelief; yet if they be not of the ſame kind with thoſe which have moved the preſent powers to alter the former <hi>Government</hi> into this which now is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what have you gained to your ſelf by your reproof, but the guilt and diſcredit of a raſh cenſurer? and what good have you done to him whom you have unadviſedly cenſured upon a wrong ground, but to make him averſe from hearing you any further? as for my ſelf I ſhall fully grant what you ſay, that the Rule whereby private men are obliged to keep their <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> muſt be obſerved in States proportionally <hi>caeteris paribus, that though they ſwear to their hurt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">How States are bound to their Oaths.</note> 
               <hi>they muſt not change, and that it is more ſafe to keep with God, although ſeemingly we run upon peril, then to quit the ways of God for prevention of peril.</hi> Theſe maxims I do fully agree unto, and am much perſwaded that none of the godly men who have had a hand in this change of Government will contradict the ſame; and becauſe I am bound to believe this of them ſo long as nothing doth appear to the contrary: therefore I muſt repreſent unto my ſelf, that which alſo I offer to your ingenuity to conſider, that it is more charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſay of them that they intended not to conſult with fleſh and blood, but with their Conſcience and duty, when they took their lives in their hands to ſee juſtice executed: and if touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any of them hereafter any thing, contrary to this judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of charity, ſhould break forth as a matter of conviction, fit to be brought home unto his Conſcience, I ſhall be ſo much the more fit to make him ſenſible of it, by how much I have had the better opinion, and never was inclined to wrong him by any evil ſurmiſes in my thoughts, for why ſhould I think evil in my
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:165758:21"/>heart of men unknown to me? of men who are my Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, in publick truſt over me? and of men whoſe actions can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not only bear ſome plea; but in the plea (if matters of fact be found true) there is nothing irrational and contrary to the grounds of natural equity.</p>
            <p>As for the Example of <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the <hi>Elders</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the chief buſineſs to be heeded therein (in my apprehenſion) is this,<note place="margin">How Joſhua was bound to his Oath made to the Gibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onites.</note> that we ſhould obſerve the true account why <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the <hi>Elders</hi> did ſtand to their <hi>Covenant</hi> with the <hi>Gibeonites:</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the murmuring of the <hi>Congregation</hi> againſt them; for the <hi>Congregation</hi> might juſtly have alledged not thoſe ſlight and trivial matters which you mention, but the invalidity and nullity of the Oath it ſelf, that it was <hi>ipſo facto</hi> void, as being a tranſgreſſion of the <hi>Commandement</hi> of <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 20.15.16.17.</note> who had forbidden the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to enter into league with any of the people of the Land, or to ſuffer them to remain alive in it.</p>
            <p>Moreover, that the main circumſtance and expreſs ground of their contract with the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> was a meer nullity, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to be a deceit; for the contract was made with this expreſs condition, that the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> were none of the People of the Land, which being found otherwiſe, the contract was void.</p>
            <p>To this plea of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> what you would have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered I know not; but ſome <hi>Divines</hi> of good note confeſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe grounds, that the <hi>Oath</hi> which was made to the <hi>Gibeon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites</hi> was void <hi>de jure,</hi> and that <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the <hi>Elders</hi> were not bound to keep it, yet that <hi>de facto</hi> they reſolved up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on equitable Conſiderations to keep it <hi>ex parte tantùm;</hi> for that it was notkept <hi>ex toto</hi> is apparent; for it was kept only as to the main matter which was the <hi>promiſe of life,</hi> but as to the matter of <hi>freedom</hi> and <hi>confederacy,</hi> which is implyed in the termes of <hi>Peace, and of a League with them. Joſh.</hi> 9. <hi>verſe</hi> 15. it was not kept; and yet the promiſe of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and confederation was no leſs covenanted with them then that of life. Now the equitable conſiderations which moved the <hi>Princes</hi> thus to qualifie the contract, and not to make it whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly void, were as I conceive, the reſpect due to the <hi>Oath by the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:165758:22"/>Lord God of Iſrael, verſe</hi> 19. and to their own ſafety, <hi>leaſt wrath be upon us, verſe</hi> 20. ſay they added the ſin of wrath breaking their <hi>Oath:</hi> they were not free from guilt for ſwearing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking Councel with God: if now they ſhould ſeem not at all to reſpect their <hi>Oath,</hi> this might heighten that guilt to bring forth a puniſhment, and I believe we ſhall do them no wrong, if we conjecture that they did conſider alſo this incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencie, that if they ſhould wholly have diſregarded their <hi>Oath,</hi> a diſreſpect would have been brought thereby deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly not only upon themſelves in point of fidelity, but alſo up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the name of <hi>God,</hi> in point of reverence in the minds of the <hi>Nations,</hi> who ſhould have heard of this their breach of <hi>Oath</hi> but not have been able to know the grounds of the juſtifiableneſs thereof; for it was not poſſible ſuddenly (as matters then ſtood between them and Neighbour-Nations) to inform them of the juſt reaſons of their not keeping their <hi>Oath;</hi> and to think that in equity this might have ſwayed ſomewhat with them is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable. But the main thing which did caſt the ballance is clearly that which in the Text is alledged, the equity of ſaving their life; for being in a ſtrait by reaſon of their raſh <hi>Oath,</hi> they followed that which was moſt ſafe, not wholly to diſanul their promiſe, but to keep that part thereof which was moſt favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſpare their lives; but the other part by which they ſhould have been exempted from the condition of <hi>Bond-men,</hi> and made <hi>Confederates,</hi> was made void, although the <hi>Oath</hi> did no doubt include this promiſe as well as the other. So that <hi>de facto</hi> this part of the <hi>Oath</hi> being altered lawfully, it ſheweth that the other <hi>de jure</hi> might alſo have been altered, if the juſt fear of greater inconveniencies which might have followed upon the alteration, then upon the confirmation thereof, had not ſwayed with them: therefore upon more mature thoughts, this part of the <hi>Oath</hi> not being altered, but deliberately confirmed, it was made for ever afterward unalterable, and this confirmation of the <hi>Oath,</hi> as to that part which ſecured their lives, being viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Saul</hi> for worldly ends, and for ſuch conſiderations as you wrongfully think my grounds allow, was puniſhed by <hi>God</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Family; for the promiſe of life to the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> being afterward ratified, not only by the <hi>Princes,</hi> but by the <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:165758:22"/>alſo, when they had been three hundred years, or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about in poſſeſſion of their right, there could be no colour for <hi>Saul</hi> to perſecute them to death; for although they ſhould have had none other plea, but ſo long a preſcription of time for their right to a livelihood in their ſervice, I know not how in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, it could have been taken from them.</p>
            <p>I conceive then that the firſt contract with the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> was not binding, and that <hi>Joſhua</hi> in dealing afterward with them,<note place="margin">Two ſoveral Contracts with the Gibeonites.</note> did bring them to be ſenſible of this, as it appeareth by their confeſſion, and the reſignation of themſelves to his diſcretion, <hi>v.</hi> 24.25. begging their lives, and not claiming any right to it by contract: it appeareth alſo not to have been binding <hi>de jure</hi> out of <hi>v.</hi> 14. where the Text ſaith, they asked not councel at the mouth of God, to intimate the neglect of reſpect due to God, and the tranſgreſſion of his revealed will in the buſineſs, which clearly made the matter in it ſelf a nullity: So that the <hi>Congregation,</hi> if they had executed the ſentence of death, which God by <hi>Moſes</hi> had denounced againſt them, could not have been counted tranſgreſſors againſt God, notwithſtanding the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the <hi>Elders;</hi> but then it would have been counted cruelty in the <hi>Congregation,</hi> and breach of <hi>Oath</hi> in the <hi>Elders,</hi> and a diſreſpect in the people towards the <hi>Engagement</hi> of their <hi>Princes,</hi> and many other inconveniencies beſides would have followed in reference to men and their interpretation of that action, if no equitable temperament had been found in the buſineſs, which upon a ſecond Treaty (the firſt being declared void) was done with the conſent of the <hi>Congregation:</hi> and this ſecond Contract <hi>God</hi> did ratifie, as appeareth by the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Saul</hi> for the breach of it.</p>
            <p>Thus you have my ſenſe of the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Joſhua</hi> to the <hi>Gibeon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites;</hi> which in many and main things is different from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent caſe; only I have been thus large upon it, to prevent your miſtake leſt you ſhould think (as I know ſome do) the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract <hi>de jure</hi> binding, becauſe confirmed by an <hi>Oath;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon infer by this preſident, that an <hi>Oath</hi> is indiſſoluble, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be made to eſtabliſh a thing materially unlawful; and although it may fall out to oblige to ſomething literally, which is contrary to the main intent thereof. Now I hold that if a thing once ſworn, become either materially or formerly unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:165758:23"/>or by change of circumſtances impoſſible to be done, that then the Oath is no more binding, but <hi>ipſo facto</hi> extinct.</p>
            <p>In that matter which is ſaid to pinch my friend, and my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to it; you conſider two things. Firſt, becauſe I ſay of thoſe who have made this change in the <hi>Government,</hi> that they will plead for themſelves; and becauſe I take not upon me profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly to juſtifie their proceedings, you conclude (but moſt ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationally) that I condemn them for <hi>Covenant-breakers;</hi> but there is no equitable and ingenuous Reader, who can conſtrue any thing out of any words of mine, which will yield ſuch a concluſion; for I profeſs it is wholly againſt my Conſcience, to do as you do, <hi>viz.</hi> to make my ſelf a Judge, and out of my ſphere to define matters this or that way concerning them; but you ſeem willing to catch at any thing to diſcredit them, which I ſee no warrant to do.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when I ſhew my Friend that the conſequence which he made (<hi>thus if I take</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Engagement, then I ſhall be acceſſory-to the breach of Covenant which I apprehend o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are guilty of</hi>) was not good; you are much diſpleaſed at me for it, and intend to make not only an obſervation, but an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimadverſion upon my diſcourſe concerning that matter: let me firſt repreſent briefly the ſubſtance of my reaſon which you ſeem not at all to take notice of, and then I ſhall take notice of, your animadverſion.</p>
            <p>I ſhew that his inference was not good,<note place="margin">Why no man by the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement can be acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſory to other mens ſins (if they have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) for make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a change in the State.</note> from the direct and plain matter of the <hi>Engagement,</hi> lookt upon in the letter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which binds us to nothing elſe, but to procure the good of the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> as now it ſtands, and this I ſay at all times is a duty to be done, however it ſtands: I ſay alſo, that to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and do this, is agreeable to the intent of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> from whence to my underſtanding, is clearly inferred, that the taking of the <hi>Engagement</hi> to this effect, can be no breach of the <hi>Covenant</hi> which doth allow of this as a duty; for if the plain du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Engagement</hi> is that which the main intent and deſign of the <hi>Covenant</hi> doth preſuppoſe, then the obligation to that can be no breach of this, and conſequently his inference is not good; for it is clear that the <hi>Covenant</hi> obliging us to ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular duties of truth and faithfulneſs towards the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:165758:23"/>as it was then eſtabliſhed with a <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Houſe of Lords,</hi> cannot bind us up, from promiſing and intending to be true and faithful to the whole <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> as it is now eſtabliſhed, without a <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Houſe of Lords.</hi> The having or wanting of a <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Houſe of Lords,</hi> is but accidental to the main duty of being true and faithful to the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> as it is offered to us in the <hi>Engagement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this matter of reaſon you ſay nothing, which yet was the main thing to be ſpoken to, if you intended an animadverſion: But you tell me, <hi>that my diſcourſe doth neceſſarily imply a high charge of inconſiderateneſs in thoſe that made and impoſed the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, whereof none can believe them guilty;</hi> and this you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to make good, by telling me further what they who made and impoſed the <hi>Engagement</hi> knew, as inconſiſtent with my ſenſe of the <hi>Engagement,</hi> wherein you follow your ordinary vein, to make the worſt conſtruction you can of my ſence, and to preſume to expreſs their ſenſe and intentions little to their commendation. To diſpute with you conjecturally what their thoughts, were is no part of my duty, it is ſufficient for my aim, to evince that the plain matter of the <hi>Engagement</hi> is a clear du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty not diſagreeable to the intent of the <hi>Covenant</hi> which you o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrowe not; and therefore my anſwer to my friends ſcruple ſtands firm; for which cauſe I think it needleſs to ſpend time up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the rectifying of your miſconſtruction of my ſenſe of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement,</hi> as if it meant by the duty which I preſs, only the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecal good of the Common-wealth,</hi> and had no reſpect at all to the extrinſecal good thereof, and to the clauſe <hi>as it is now eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.</hi> Nor ſhall I inſiſt to make an animadverſion upon your miſapplication of this miſconceived ſenſe of mine, as if I took the <hi>Engagement</hi> in ſo large a ſignification, as that any man might foment under the words thereof what intentions he would, though never ſo deſtructive to the preſent <hi>Eſtabliſhment:</hi> theſe things I ſhall paſs by, becauſe I ſuppoſe no candid Reader will ſo underſtand me, but will eaſily perceive that you frame to your ſelf fictious abſurdities upon miſconſtrued notions.</p>
            <p>The obſervation which you make upon my interpretation
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:165758:24"/>of the words <hi>without a King and Houſe of Lords,</hi> which I call <hi>an explication of the words (now eſtabliſhed) immediatly going before, and not an abſolute abnegation of the things lookt upon barely as in themſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Whether the words with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a King and Houſe of Lords are an abnegation of them, barely and as in themſelves.</note> hath ſomewhat a better colour of reaſon, then that which you mentioned before; and although I make no ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of that acceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe words, as to ſtand confidently up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, that they cannot rationally bear any other interpretation; (for ſuppoſe they may by ſome conſequence imply an abnega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> Houſe, how will that oppoſe my aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? or prejudice my reaſoning with my Friend? yet your ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing againſt the abnegation of them ſo as I have mentioned, is not valid: for firſt, you take not up my expreſſions as they are delivered by me, and ſo contradict not my aſſertion, for you contradict only <hi>an abſolute negation of the things themſelves,</hi> and I aſſert, that the words do not mean, <hi>an abſolute abnegation of the things lookt upon, harely as in themſelves.</hi> I make a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the negation of a thing and the abnegation of it. I may deny a thing to have a being, when it is not exiſtent <hi>in rerum natura:</hi> and yet not intend to renounce all reſpect which may be had to it, lookt upon barely in it ſelf. I may confeſs that a thing is not in this or that reſpect, and yet not declare that I caſt it off, barely in it ſelf, and in all reſpects. Now I ſay that the [meaning of the] words of the <hi>Engagement</hi> in their proper and obvious ſence import not the laſt, but only the firſt acception, where I would have you to take notice that the ſence which you aſſert is not proper and obvious, but brought in upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny conſequences, which though not irrational, yet not contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory to what I ſay. Again in my expreſſions, the words <hi>barely as in themſelves</hi> (for the word <hi>truly</hi> is not rightly printed, it ſhould be <hi>barely</hi>) are reduplicatives, and you take them up without any reduplication, and ſpeak <hi>of the things themſelves.</hi> Now there is a great difference between a thing in a reflexive ſenſe or reduplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive conſideration, &amp; between the direct notion of it, you take up my words as if I ſpoke of a <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Houſe of Lords</hi> themſelves, that is in a direct notion, and I clearly ſpeak of them in a redupli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catve notion, <hi>barely as in themſelves:</hi> therefore you contradict not what I ſay, although you pretend to ſhew that my gloſs (as you call it) carries a full contradiction in it ſelf: it is true, that your wrong allegation of the gloſs doth ſeem to make it
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:165758:24"/>contradictory by way of conſequences to the Text; but how it hath a full contradiction in it ſelf, you make it not at all appear. And this is the firſt point of your miſtake in the wrong allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my words, and the non-obſerving that I ſpeak of a proper and obvious ſenſe of the <hi>Engagement,</hi> and not of a ſenſe by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence. The ſecond is the invalidity of your conſequence, as to my underſtanding; for you ſay, that the words as now <hi>eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> do fully imply that abnegation of <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> Houſe which I there mention, becauſe the adverb <hi>now</hi> in the <hi>Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (ſay you) doth ſtand in full oppoſition to the face of things in former <hi>Adminiſtrations.</hi> I grant that <hi>now</hi> ſtands in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to time paſt by way of conſequence, but not in a direct and proper <hi>Notion;</hi> for I may look upon things as now eſtabliſhed, without looking back and comparing them with that which hath been; but when you ſay, that <hi>as now</hi> is a full contradiction to my ſenſe <hi>as ever,</hi> I confeſs I underſtand not that, for if <hi>as ever,</hi> doth in its proper and obvious notion, and in my ſenſe compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all times paſt, preſent and to come, then I know not by what good conſequence it can be ſaid to be a full contradiction to that which is preſent; for that which is <hi>ever</hi> muſt needs alſo be <hi>now,</hi> or elſe is <hi>not ever.</hi> I confeſs that the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> as now eſtabliſhed, hath voted down the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> houſe, and declared that at preſent they are unfit to have any ſhare or hand in the <hi>Government</hi> of this <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and in this ſenſe by the words of the <hi>Engagement,</hi> we deny them to have a being in this preſent eſtabliſhment, which is all that rationally by our Superiours (I ſpeak it with reſpect) can be deſired, and in an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious ſenſe is offered by the words of the <hi>Engagement;</hi> but from hence doth not follow, that <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> are voted down, being lookt upon barely as in themſelves; for it is clear, that the <hi>Declaration</hi> all along hath a reſpect to the ſafety of this <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth</hi> at preſent, to ſhew the inconſiſtency of a <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> Houſe with it; and ſo much I conceive may be inferred, that the <hi>Engagement</hi> doth imply by conſequence a conſent in the <hi>Subſcribers</hi> to this, but that either the <hi>Declaration,</hi> by which <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> were voted down, or the <hi>Engagement</hi> doth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige any man to aſſert that <hi>Monarchical Government</hi> in it ſelf, or <hi>Ariſtocraticall Power</hi> mixed with it, and lookt upon in it ſelf, is for ever to be rejected out of a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and that neither
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:165758:25"/>of them can conſiſt with the ſafety thereof, is much more then was ever, (as I conceive) intended by thoſe that made the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement,</hi> or then can rationally and equitably (I ſay again with reſpect) be impoſed upon any men of judgement by their <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers:</hi> nor is it at all needful to oblige Subjects to any ſuch aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, for the end for which the <hi>Engagement</hi> is offered, which is only to give the preſent powers an aſſurance of fidelity to the preſent <hi>State;</hi> but you and ſome others of your ſtrain ſeem wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſcrue up the ſenſe of the words to ſuch irrationalities as theſe are by forced conſequences, that an <hi>Odium</hi> may fall upon the preſent <hi>Government,</hi> as if they were ſet againſt <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Aristocraty,</hi> rather for ſome ſelf-ends, then for the preſent good of this <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> which to intend (if there be any ſuch leaven in the bottom) is far from the duty both of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and of a good <hi>Subject,</hi> who ſhould make the beſt conſtruction of the actions of their Superiours, and refer unto them the judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature and management of publick affairs, as they ſhall think it moſt expedient, which if my Friend would lay to heart as he ought, and practiſe accordingly he would ſoon find himſelf eaſd of any thing which in this kind might pinch him.</p>
            <p>I go on, not (as you ſay) <hi>diſcerning that which is ſaid will not hold; for you ſee it holds invincibly,</hi> but <hi>ex abundanti,</hi> yielding ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to my Friends weakneſs, more then perhaps was needful, <hi>I ſuppoſe in his apprehenſion of matters, that this Engagement doth materially ſettle ſomething in the Common-wealth, which is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the intention which he had in taking the Covenant; yet I ſay that by giving his aſſent thereunto as matters now ſtand, he doth not at all break his Covenant, becauſe the obligation to thoſe matters by vertue of the Covenant was exſtinct, before he was called upon to take the Engagement,</hi> to this you ſay, <hi>that this oppoſition of mine is wholly yielded by others, both that the Engagement is in full oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Covenant and other Oaths (and ſo all my labour loſt in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to reconcile them) and that this which I now bring, is only held out for a plea to carry it in the affirmative, that the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement may be entered, malè res agitur</hi> (ſay you) <hi>cùm tot opus eſt remediis.</hi> To which I anſwer, <hi>malè cum ijs agitur quibus tot applicanda ſunt remedia:</hi> it ſhews that their Diſeaſe may be brought to be ſtubborn, <hi>ſed benè cum ijs agitur quibus tot ſuppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunt remedia:</hi> it ſhews that no cure is wanting, though the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:165758:25"/>diſeaſe may ſeem deſperate; for if the ſuppoſition which I make were wholly yielded unto as I make it, there would be no full oppoſition between the Covenant and other oaths found, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then in the miſtaken apprehenſions of ſome that ſcare themſelves at the Engagement without a juſt cauſe my labour therefore is not loſt if things miſunderſtood may be rectified, as ſurely they may, and I hope by this time in ſome degree are. You admit, that that which is extinct &amp; made void can no more oblige, with this limitation; provided that thoſe who are obliged have no hand in extinguiſhing that which doth oblige them,<note place="margin">Corcerning the matter of an Oath how it may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed, or not extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed.</note> to worke out their own diſobligation, this limitation I do admit, and your inſtance in Davids caſe to Jonathan for preſerving his ſeed, I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. Yet if God had appointed Mephiboſheth to dye, and David to have given the ſentence in the way of juſtice, do you thinke that David would have been guilty of the breach of oath made to Jonathan for the preſerving of his ſeed? it is true we ſay the King dyes not; that is, the ſupream executioner of Laws dyes not; but the King in his perſon was <hi>Civiliter mortuus,</hi> as to his office when he was Voted cloſe priſoner in the Iſle of Wight, and if there was juſt cauſe for it in the Judgement of the Supreame power of the Nation, their oath for his preſervation being limitted to a condition, they will be able to anſwer before a higher Judge then you or I for what they have done. The caſe which I ſuppoſe is concerning a private man, who is no Judge in publique affaires, who had no hand in ſentencing him; and therefore although in the preface of the Covenant, mention is made of the King and his Poſterity, yet by his death the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the oath relating to him is extinct, and by the cauſe of his death the Law hath involved his poſterity. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/>
            </p>
            <p>That which you ſay here concerning Parliament-Priviledges, being always the ſame and unalterable, is onely ſaid and not proved; in like mauner when you tell me that we have now no Parliament actually exiſting, you begge the Queſtion, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the fundamental poſition of a full Houſe to be in the number of forty Truſtees, which I believe may be ſix times told in the Liſt of thoſe that now preſent themſelves to that Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. Your compariſon of a Phiſitian who cannot preſerve, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he recover ſtrength, doth ſuppoſe many things which are
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:165758:26"/>not granted; therefore I ſhall not think them worthy of any larger anſwer then to tell you, that the Covenant never meant that private men of whom I ſpeak ſhould be Judges of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-priviledges, or Phiſitians to the publick diſeaſes of the State. Now whether my friend hath any juſt cauſe to ſcruple further; neither you nor I are competent Judges, but the impartial Reader the third man, to whom, and to your own ſecond thoughts I ſhall leave this matter.</p>
            <p>Upon the ſecond part of my diſcourſe to my friend, you make ſome obſervations, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> wherein you rather touch matters as it were in <hi>tranſcurſu,</hi> exceptiouſly, then pitch upon a ſettled exception.</p>
            <p>You tell me firſt, that <hi>in ſtead of cleering the title of the preſent Powers as juſt and lawful, and acquitting it from uſurpation, I make it unlawful to inquire and determine concerning it.</hi> To this I ſay,<note place="margin">what the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects is to their ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors.</note> till you make it appear that it is lawful for every private man to judge definitively of the Titles, Rights and Actions of the Powers that are over him, ſo as to oblige his Conſcience to abſtain from all lawful actings in his Calling under them, till he be ſatisfied in all his ſcruples concerning them, I muſt ſtill for mine own part abſtain from preſuming to be their Judge in ſuch matters, and diſwade others from that practiſe, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them to do their own affaires quietly, and pray to God for their ſuperiour Powers.</p>
            <p>Then you blame me for holding forth the Rule by which I walk; as <hi>if I did</hi> intend to make my ſelf in all things my friends preſident, or ſuppoſed him to be ready to follow me in all things. I ſee nothing can be ſo well meant and done but it may be ill taken, when men ſeek to make exceptions and not to edifie; I thought the beſt way of edification was to hold forth the rules by which God doth teach us to walk; and becauſe I would have no man to follow me further then he ſeeth a Rule, therefore I am interpreted to have an ambition to get followers: truly I ſhall follow you gladly if you will ſhew me your Rule to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the word of God, and why ſhew you not a fault in the Rule it ſelf, if it is lyable to exceptions; but if you can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept nothing againſt it, why are you not ſo ingenous as to beare witneſs to the Truth? but when we hunt after contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:165758:26"/>this is the Genius which leads us; we look not to the thing but to experiences, and in their wrong and worſt ſide, afterward you ſay that I have been found a tranſgreſſor of mine own Rule. I ſee you allude to that which you ſaid in your ſecond exception but when you ſhall have anſwered that which I have ſaid there to rectifie your miſtakes, then you will give me cauſe to think that you have a mind not onely to tell me that I have tranſreſſed my Rule, but alſo to redreſs either me or my <hi>Rule</hi> if either be faulty; for which I ſhall thank you when you intend it as you ought to do.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Character of AntiChriſt you deny nothing of that which I ſay, but you deſire me to take it into my ſerious conſideration to whom that Character doth belong; <hi>whether to thoſe that ſeek out carefully to what power it is they owe juſtly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection that they may ſubmit themſelves thereunto, or to him who doth peremptorily determine of the forfeiture of Rights in thoſe that before were poſeſſed of an undoubted title,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concerning the ſpirit that exalts itſelf above Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, where it appeares moſt.</note> 
               <hi>and diſobliging Subjects from their Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I ſay that I have conſidered ſeriouſly the matter, and find that the anſwer is eaſie, if the Caſe be ſtated as you offer it, upon a miſtake in the ſecond part, but let the Caſe be truly ſtated, and then conſider you alſo where the Character of a Spirit exalting it ſelf above Magiſtrates doth moſt appear: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in him that ſubmits himſelf to the higher Powers which God hath actualy ſet over him, and without diſputing their title or making himſelf a Judge of their actions, doth all things juſt and lawful in his place under them as under the Ordinance of God, becauſe he doth believe that all Supream powers that are actually exiſtent in the world are ordained of God, and ought to be ſubmitted unto as Gods Vice-gerents in their places for Conſcience ſake? or in him that doth nothing of all this, but making himſelf a Judge of the Powers that are over him and of their proceedings, doth reſiſt them as Uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, denying all obedience even in the beſt and lawfulleſt things commanded for publick ſafety by them: doth deſpiſe their government, and ſpeak evil of their dignity, and doth admit of none to have the right to Supream power but whom he hath determined ſhould have it? which of theſe hath moſt of the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:165758:27"/>ſpirit of Antichriſt judge ye? As for that which you call <hi>a peremptory determination of the forfeiture of Right in thoſe that were before poſſe eſſed of an undoubted title,</hi> I can ſay this to it, that if you can ſhew me that I make any peremptory deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of any thing in particular, I ſhall confeſs a fault, but if I do nothing more then repreſent the undenyable cleere &amp; general grounds of natural equity, upon which Rights may be forfeited, without making any ſpecial application thereof un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to circumſtances, or pronouncing a definitive ſentence for or againſt any, as a Judge in the Caſe, then your cenſure will be found unjuſt and inconſiderate, and to ſee your errour in it, look upon that which I have ſaid unto your ſecond obſervation.</p>
            <p>To the judgement of Diſcretion which I allow with a limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> 
               <hi>that it ought not to be ſet up ſo high within ourſelves or over others, as to oblige our Conſcience to follow it as the onely Rule, and drown the thoughts of all other rules in point of obedience to the powers who are viſibly over us; you ſay that blind obedience is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then ſuch uſe of light, that when I believe I ſee my way, I have no allowance to follow it.</hi> This is a great miſtake of my meaning, for ſo far as I allow to judge, I allow to follow light, I allow to judge, that is to diſcerne and obſerve rationally who are in the viſible poſſeſſion of ſuperiority, how they declare their own right, and with what power they ſtand; theſe things muſt be taken notice of, that men may be able to judge their own preſent ſtation under whom they ſtand, whom God hath ſet over them,<note place="margin">Concerning the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, &amp; a definitive judgement, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout what matters they are conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant.</note> and unto whom they owe obedience for Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake: ſo far as this judgement doth diſcover actual ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority, I oblige the conſcience of every man in his particular act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions to walk in the light thereof as a dutiful Subject; but I allow him not in the diſquiry of matters concerning his ſuperiors to go ſo far as to judge peremptorily of their proceedings in their places, whether they do right or wrong, and whether their title be good or bad; in theſe things, becauſe he cannot have that light which is requiſit to ſettle a definitive judgement therein, and becauſe he is not called to be a Judge of ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, therefore I allow him not to oblige his Conſcience to be intangled into any ſuch judicature, or to ſuſpend the acts of his civil and Chriſtian obedience (wherein Conſcience is to follow
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:165758:27"/>other cleere Rules) upon his own or other mens obſervations of ſuch things. In a word, I allow all men to ſeek out their way, and when they have found it to follow it conſcionably: but they are to be directed, that in ſeeking their way they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume not above their line; their Line is to diſcerne to whom they owe the duty of a Subject, &amp; what the thing is which by their ſuperiours is required of them, whether it be anſwerable to the Law of God and nature, yea or no? within this line their judgement is to walk for themſelves; but beyond this Line to make ſuch obſervations of their Superiours ways, or to give way to the apprehenſions which may be ſuggeſted unto them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſame from others, ſo far as to make thoſe obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and apprehenſions a rule to their conſcience to walk by, is in my judgement irregular, and the very ſnare wherein at this time you and many others are taken in unawares, whiles you diſtinguiſh not between your own line and the line of others, and btween the judgement of diſcretion &amp; peremptory judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which are to be exerciſed about different objects and have a different relation unto Conſcience, the things whereof I am no competent judge, I may diſeern, with an obſervation of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> leaving the determination thereof unto others to whom the judicature properly belongeth</p>
            <p>Concerning the Rule which I give, whereby Superiours may be diſcerned as agreeable to ſenſe, to reaſon, and to conſcience, you object,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That if <hi>this Rule were right, Iſrael whenſoever they were made Servants to their enemies, to Cuſhan Ruſhataim, to Eglon, to Jabin, to Midian, to Ammon, and to the Philiſtims, ſhould have been bound up in bondage from ſeeking deliverance, nor any endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour muſt have been uſed to recover loſt rights.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between a State and v private man, in oppoſing oppreſſive powers over them.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, that this doth not follow at all.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the caſe of a private man is not the ſame with a whole <hi>ſtate,</hi> this hath a right to govern it ſelf independently, but no pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man in a <hi>State</hi> can pretend unto this: therefore a <hi>State</hi> may endeavour to recover its right and liberty whenſoever it can get ſtrength to caſt off the Government which is over it; but no privat man may intend to make himſelf independent from all ſuperiour powers; he ought then to take notice of thoſe that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:165758:28"/>God hath ſet over him, to do his duty towards them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In a whole <hi>State,</hi> when it is oppreſſed by Forraigners, as when God ſent thoſe enemies to bring <hi>Iſrael</hi> into bondage there was no doubt, or need of a Rule to know who were their ſuperiours; but here a particular man is ſuppoſed in a civil divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to be in doubt between two competitors, to whom he is to perform the duty of a Subject: the Rule then is only fitted for this caſe, and not for the other.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the deliverance of <hi>Iſrael</hi> from the oppreſſion of their enemies it is ſaid, that God <hi>raiſed them up Judges, and that he was with the Judge whom he raiſed, Jud.</hi> 2.16.18. therefore it followeth, that he put publick Authority upon their deliverers, and conſequently, that he did not allow private men to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then in ſubjection, as when he brought <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> who brought them away Captive into <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> he did Command all private men to be in ſubjection, <hi>and to pray for the peace of the place where they were Captives;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.7.</note> even as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth injoyn all <hi>Chriſtians to be ſubject to the Roman Emperours</hi> (<hi>Rom.</hi> 13.) who for the moſt part were all u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">How Subjects are to behave themſelves towards theſe Powers, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther claiming ſuperiority by Contract or by Conqueſt.</note> you object againſt that which I ſay about a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract</hi> which makes a Law between <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Subjects,</hi> and a <hi>Conqueſt</hi> which is bound to no <hi>Law,</hi> that it <hi>were worth obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if I would acquaint you, which way the preſent powers do claim.</hi> I anſwer, my Councel is, which way ſoever you are to look to your duty, and not to reſiſt the Ordinance of God which is over you: uſe your own diſcretion to obſerve what you can, without making your ſelf a peremptory Judge of their way: and what I adviſe you to do, I endeavour to obſerve my ſelf: therefore it is not reaſonable that you ſhould deſire me to tranſgreſs mine own <hi>Rule,</hi> and go beyond my line to define other mens affairs which they have not called me to determine. I can diſcern a mixture in their way; to ſome they uſe the right of Conquerors, to others they walk by the <hi>Rule</hi> of a <hi>Contract:</hi> you may put your ſelf in either relation, for as your behaviour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them is, ſo you are like to find them.</p>
            <p>Concerning the <hi>Queries</hi> whereof you ſay the <hi>Queſtion</hi> is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably begged, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> I have no more to ſay, but that I ſpeak there in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:165758:28"/>the name of others, and that it is left to your diſcretion to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider thoſe <hi>Queries</hi> as the matter of them is offered in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a plea for thoſe who are accuſed of uſurpation.</p>
            <p>And although you ſay,<note place="margin">Concerning the Queries mentioned in the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, how they are to be reflected upon.</note> you have never <hi>ſeen ſo much as an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt for the proof of that which is taken as granted in theſe Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries;</hi> yet I can tell you that I have met with thoſe that have in the preſence of many, undertaken the proof thereof, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it relates to matters of fact, whereof I can bear no infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble witneſs <hi>pro</hi> or <hi>contra:</hi> therefore I muſt leave it without a definitive ſentence, as not being obliged in Conſcience this or that way to a judicature, and yet I may rationally with an indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent eye be inclined to aſſent more one way then another, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes keeping my affection entire to the rule of my duty; for what ever the matters of fact be in other mens adminiſtrations, that is no rule to me in my ſphere, I muſt look to the proper rule of mine own work with a reſpect to the matter and end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond branch of my friends doubt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> that which I offer (as a rule whereby to reſolve his Conſcience in the ſcruple it had you meddle not withall, but to avoid the evidence of that rule, you put another caſe and tell me. <hi>But if the Engagement be not a duty as men affected to the common cauſe of liberty (by mine own conceſſions) are perſwaded, then (ſay you) guilt will follow upon ſuch ſuppoſition which I have laid down.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concerning the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that it is a Duty; and what doth follow thereupon.</note> To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that no man hath ever yet denyed the Engagement to be a duty in the ſence wherein I underſtand it, nor you yourſelf, although through prejudice againſt the preſent Rulers you are loath they ſhould be underſtood to tender it in that ſenſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I offer it. Seeing then the Engagement in the ſenſe in which I take it is undoubtedly a duty iuſt to be required by the preſent Powers, you deale not rationally to ſuppoſe it to be no duty, except you had ſhewed that either it could not beare the ſenſe wherein I take it, or that that ſenſe is not a matter of duty now to be performed as that it is unjuſt to be required: nothing of which you having done, and yet taking it for granted to be no duty (onely becauſe I confeſs that ſome men well affected to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty are ſo perſwaded, though it is cleere that I think them to be in an error) you ſeeme cleerely to beg the queſtion
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:165758:29"/>which is between us after that I have proved it; for having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Engagement to be a duty, and ſuch a duty as is fundamental to all other former bonds; I may lawfully make it a ground to build ſome inferences thereon, and you not having diſproved it to be what I ſay it is, have no ground to build any contrary inferences thereupon. Then alſo the infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which you make is, to my conception (if I take your mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) needleſs; <hi>If</hi> (ſay <hi>you</hi>) <hi>it is no Duty, then guilt will follow upon ſuch ſuppoſition which you have laid down,</hi> you had done well to have ſhewed what the ſuppoſition is which you mean, for I cannot well gueſs at it. If you mean that the guilt of being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſory to other mens faults (whereof the queſtion is) will follow upon the ſuppoſition that the Engagement is a duty when as indeed it is none; this may be granted, but is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly mentioned, becauſe my preſuppoſal that the doing of a duty can make no man acceſſory to another mans perſonal fault, doth ſufficiently include; that if the thing done by him be not a duty, it will not excuſe him from being acceſſory unto his fault.</p>
            <p>You take notice of the expreſſion wherein I ſay of ſome, <hi>that they deſerve not to have a being in the Common-wealth,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> and you call it <hi>a high one, and a paſſing of ſentence upon thoſe that have forborn to ſubſcribe this Engagement, being conſcious to themſelves of the bonds of former Engagemenns.</hi> Herein you give us an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of that way of apprehending things which is in the ſpirits of all men who are led by prejudice, for although the matter which I deliver is as cleere a truth as any that can be thought upon in the way of morality, and relates to no particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons at all,<note place="margin">An inſtance of a prejudicate way of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interpreting plaine truths.</note> but mentions only a general and undenyable maxim, which is a principle of all human ſocietys; yet you cannot looke ſtraightly, and with a ſingle eye upon it as it is delivered, but through the Proſpective of your prejudice you not only pervert my meaning, but relat my words otherwiſe then I do offer them; for I ſay, that this is a rule of juſtice, that all men are bound to ſhew fidelity <hi>unto thoſe of whom they deſire protection, and that we ure bound to be ready to every good worke towards thoſe with whom we live. which is all that in the preſent ſtate of this Common-wealth is required of us; which if we deſire not to performe. we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve not to have a being in it,</hi> theſe truths which I deliver as generall maxims, and apply them to myſelf as well as to others,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:165758:29"/>and univerſally to all men in all Common-wealths in the world, becauſe you cannot deny either the premiſes or their cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rrnce. You carp at the clauſe thereof; you call it a high ſentence, and to make me odious you relate it as if I ſpake it onely of thoſe that have forborne to ſubſcribe the Engagement, which proceeds from a narrowneſs of ſpirit, which cannot look upon the face of univerſal Truths as in themſelves they are offered to the underſtanding, without turning them awry to ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al application. And becauſe your diſcourſe which followeth hereupon (concerning the inconveniency of proceeding in ſo high a way, and concerning other things, whereof you make your ſelf a Judge and a Councellour of State, rather to reprove then to intreat, and in a loving manner to adviſe that which is equitable) is all grounded upon this diſtorted apprehenſion of my words; I ſhall leave it as a matter in which I am not at all concerned, deſiring you to judge equitably whether upon ſuch a tryal of your inclination to miſunderſtand and miſreport plain words, ſo full of cleere truth contrary to my ſenſe, I have not ſufficient cauſe to warn you, and juſtly to be jealous over you, leaſt you be no leſs injurious to your Superiors, and to all that which they do towards the publick by miſinterpreting the ſame towards others then you are to me, and how far ſuch a ſtrain is different from the ſpirit of Chriſt, and from the way of doing good to others, I ſhall ſeriouſly refer unto your more quiet and conſcionable conſideration, deſiring you to weigh it by your ſelf at better leaſure as in the preſence of God. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/>
            </p>
            <p>The deſcourſe which you make upon my diſcription of the end of the Engagement, which you call a gloſs; is almoſt of the ſame ſtrain with this immediatly going before, the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is onely, that here the words are not ſo miſreported, but by miſconſtruction of matters you wrong my meaning as much as you can by Conſequences.</p>
            <p>I ſay, that <hi>the end of the Engagement is, to give the Supreame Power an aſſurance that we ſhall not betray it, but that we are willing to maintain all good intelligence for publique concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with it, notwithſtanding the preſent changes brought upon the Common-wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:165758:30"/>
            <p>You ſay,<note place="margin">Concerning the end of the Engagement &amp; what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
               <hi>that to intend this doth utterly ſpoil all aſſurance that poſſibly can be given either to this State or any other;</hi> and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon you give (referring me to what hath been ſaid before, where I found no reaſon at all, but uncharitable ſurmiſes, <hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>Sect.</hi> 10.) is this, <hi>that if no reſpect is to be had to outward forms, but to the intrinſecal good of the Common-wealth only: then</hi> (ſay you) <hi>all are at liberty (notwithſtanding ſuch Engagement) where they will to hold intelligence; provided, that their judgements tell them that the publick is beſt provided for,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Where the obſervers conſequence is related, &amp; the anſwer thereunto ſhews the grounds of his error.</note> 
               <hi>that way in which they keep correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereunto let me for anſwer tell you,</p>
            <p>Firſt, you never heard from me, that no reſpect was to be had to outward forms; for I believe that a due and conſcionable reſpect is to be had to all outward forms, by thoſe that are in an orderly way engaged to them, ſo long as they laſt; but that any men ſhould be engaged to them after that they are altered and taken away without their default, or ſhould be obliged to practiſe the maintaining of them to the diſturbance of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick peace and welfare of a <hi>Nation,</hi> is a thing which I cannot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, or that any outward form ſhould be accompted eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to any <hi>Nation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concerning the uſe of outward formes.</note> and more then accidental, ſo that by the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme power thereof it may not be alterable upon exigent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, is another thing which doth paſs my capacity, and yet except you aſſert theſe paradoxes, you will never make out the concluſions which you aim at, for the ſenſe of former <hi>Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> as you make them obligatory to the Conſcience at this time in oppoſition to this <hi>Engagement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> you never heard from me, that the intrinſecal good of the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> only was to be intended without the outward good thereof alſo:<note place="margin">Concerning the intrinſecal and extrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal good of the Common-wealth.</note> I believe that in a <hi>Common-wealth</hi> as in a man, there is a ſoule and a body, and that in both there is a ſubſtantial and accidental good, and that this is alterable, but that that is alwayes in the eye of every one that is faithful to a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> unalterably to be ſought after, and that the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable good of a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> depends upon circumſtances, and is determinable by the ſupreme power of every <hi>Nation,</hi> I ſuppoſe you will not deny, and here I ſhall tell you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, leſt you miſtake my notion of a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> that I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:165758:30"/>by it, not an abſtract form, but a concrete ſubſtance conſiſting of the body of the <hi>Nation,</hi> as it is taken both col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectively &amp; repreſentatively; for neither of theſe are at any time to be underſtood without the other in my diſcourſes, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome relation to each other. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, you never heard from me that every private man is to be made a Judge of that which is the publick good,<note place="margin">Concerning the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men, touching the publick good.</note> as if it were free for him to follow any courſe without controle, which his judgement tells him the publick is beſt provided for; for I believe that all rational men, and honeſt <hi>Members</hi> of a <hi>Common</hi>-wealth, take that to be beſt for the publick good which the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme powers thereof declare fit to be proſecuted concerning it, according to the truſt repoſed in them; ſo that faithful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects will judge that they ought to be rationally concluded in ſuch matters by their ſuperiours. Upon theſe aſſertions I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you will be able to ſee how far you wrong my ſenſe of the end of the <hi>Engagement;</hi> and truly if you would but have been a little ingenuous, and conſidered that the preface of the <hi>Act</hi> for taking of the <hi>Engagement,</hi> doth expreſs in effect the ſame ends which I mention, you could not with any colour of reaſon have made the inferences upon it which you make: nay and the very letter of my words is cleerly contradictory to your infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; for I declare the end to be, <hi>not to betray the ſupreme pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and to be willing to maintain with it all good intelligence,</hi> and you infer, <hi>then all are at liberty, notwithſtanding ſuch Engagement to hold intelligence where they will.</hi> How can a promiſe made to theſe ſupreme powers, (who are the repreſentative <hi>Common-wealth</hi>) to be true and faithful to them; that is, not to betray them, but to maintain good intelligence for the publick welfare with them; yield this concluſion, <hi>Ergo</hi> I am free to hold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence with their enemies againſt them; if I will underſtand by the publick welfare their deſtruction? theſe are ſuch diſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a plain matter, that I wonder how you ſhould come to ſtrain your wit to beget them. There is much more of this kind of ſtuff in your following gloſſes, upon my words, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the end of the <hi>Engagement,</hi> to which I think fit to ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, for by what I have ſaid already, you will be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:165758:31"/>your ſelf, of that which I could ſay unto the remainder of thoſe your diſcourſes.</p>
            <p>That which you obſerve concerning the diſſolution of the tye of private men, to the Heir of the Crown, is, <hi>that we muſt not look unto the works of God alone, but alſo unto his word, to walk by a Rule,</hi> which I ſhall not contradict, but heartily affirm with you, and be ready to ſhew that by the word as a Rule, we pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men are bound to obey in things good and lawful the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme powers immediatly and actually over us under <hi>God,</hi> and not ſuch as are not over us whom in oppoſition unto them we may be inclined to chuſe. As for the <hi>Engagement,</hi> it doth clearly oblige us to do our duty to the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> collectively and repreſentatively without a <hi>King;</hi> but to my underſtanding the expreſſion is not ſo againſt <hi>Kingly-power</hi> in it ſelf conſidered; but that the ſupreme power of the <hi>Nation,</hi> may, if they ſee cauſe, and the publick ſafety in their judgements (for they are only the competent Judges thereof) doth require it; ſet up a <hi>King</hi> again to morrow. I do not think it in the power of any ſupreme power; if they will be faithful to their truſt to bind their own hands in ſuch a way as not to do and undo; for this would be to oblige themſelves to that which is againſt the nature of their truſt; nor is it imaginable that the <hi>Covenant</hi> or any other ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of <hi>Oath</hi> can be ſo high, as to bind us ſo to a <hi>King</hi> or his Heire, that we ſhould not be able lawfully to promiſe truth and faithfulneſs to the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> without them, when they are not in place. The example of a <hi>Child</hi> to his <hi>Father,</hi> beggs the <hi>Queſtion;</hi> and then the Lawes of men bind only to that which the letter directly imports, in reſpect of outward actions men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in them, and takes no notice of ſecret inward affections. The <hi>Argument</hi> taken from <hi>Gods</hi> way of providence after a thing is done to acquieſce in it, by doing our duty in all other things which the ſame providence doth offer, can be no occaſion to ſin, or any ſnare to do evil, nor do I preſs it any further in this caſe, but to acquieſce at things paſt, which God hath altered, and to do a duty at things preſent, which God hath ſetled, and if this <hi>Divinity</hi> will not hold in reference to private men, I pray ſhew us ſome better Rule, and we ſhall hearken to you in it.</p>
            <p>Concerning the place of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> Chap. 24. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> verſ. 21. where it is foretold that <hi>the Kings of the Earth ſhall be puniſhed and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:165758:31"/>viſited;</hi> I ſhall admit of your caveat, for I make onely a probable conjecture of that which God hath done, or intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to do amongſt us, and not a peremptory definition of that which ſhall fall out,<note place="margin">Concerning the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies what the caveat is.</note> your admonition alſo concerning the doing of our duty I willingly receive, and grant that Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies touching that which God will do; are no rules for our actions, but the Precepts touching his will which we ſhould do, muſt guide us. That which you diſcourſe, of the fulfilling of the Propheſies concerning Chriſt to be put to death by wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked hands, is a Truth; Nay, if men be wicked, and have no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to God in that which they do; although they be ſent forth with a ſpecial and expreſs command of his own upon their works, yet they do not his preſcribed will as their duty, but onely a material work wherein their aim may be undutifull. <hi>Jehu</hi> is a clear example of this.</p>
            <p>That which you bid me take into my ſerious conſideration concerning the <hi>Engagement</hi> I hope God will inable me to do; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> I can ſay it before him; that I am not conſcious to my ſelf of want of Charity, and tenderneſs to thoſe that are ſcrupled: nor do I think that this <hi>Engagement</hi> can be ſo clear to men pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingaged in other ſtrong bonds of duty which they cannot ſeediſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, and prepoſſeſſed againſt the way of the change, perhaps more then comes to their ſhare to judge of it, and of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which have brought it about; I ſay I think not that this <hi>Engagement</hi> can be ſo clear unto them,<note place="margin">The grounds of Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion towards diſſenters about the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement.</note> as that they ſhould ſuddenly without any debate in their Spirits, be carried to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of it, therefore I have alwayes been Sollicitou fors a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of proceedings; and for amiable conferences, to beget a good underſtanding of doubtfull matters whereinto by the neceſſities of the times we are fallen. I confeſs that evidence doth not alwayes go along with Truth; for to make a thing evident it muſt be offered <hi>ad modum recipientis;</hi> and although men be ſuch in whom both parts and piety are ſeen, yet ſometimes they are ſo ſhut up with prejudices wherein corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons work; that they act far below themſelves: and I dare not ſay, that in the propoſal of matters to cure them of prejudicate thoughts, there is alwayes that humility, love, Prudency and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudicants uſed to them which is able to cure their diſeaſe without any further diſtemper and inflammation to their ſores,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:165758:32"/>ſomtimes it may be truly ſaid <hi>medice cura teipſum</hi> &amp; the <hi>Apoſtles memento, Gal.</hi> 6.1. to keep us in a meek temper, <hi>leſt thou alſo be tempted</hi> is remarkable: therefore God forbid that any ſhould be preſſed to act againſt judgement, &amp; the dictates of their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence only by <hi>Club-law,</hi> who ſeek rationally to conſider things belonging to duty in the fear of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the reſiſtance of powers, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> that which you offer is worth the conſideration, and to help you to a deciſion of that which ſeemeth doubtful: I pray conſider in the Authours which are approved upon that Subject, whether any doth allow that private men without all publick reſpect,<note place="margin">Concerning reſiſtance of Powers.</note> may make ſuch a reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and about things wholly good and lawful in themſelves? as for the other queſtion, what a juſt power with right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable may challenge, is one thing, and what a private Subject under an uſurped power may do in oppoſition to the power which is actually over him, is another thing: therefore I ſhall deſire you alſo to conſider, that private mens opinions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning forfeitures of rights and uſurpations without title, are not warrantable grounds to act towards the unſettlement of the publick in oppoſition to powers that are, in plenary poſſeſſion of all places of <hi>Government.</hi> As for your requeſt in the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that <hi>thoſe who ſee not with my eyes, and cannot warrant all that I approve (having what to ſay if called unto it) may obtaine from me a more favourable cenſure then to be judged unworthy of a being in the Common-wealth, where by right of birth-right they have their freedome;</hi> I ſhall profeſs that it never came in my thoughts ſo to cenſure any,<note place="margin">Concerning mutual for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance, and the equity thereof.</note> although I cannot but aſſert this to be a fundamental truth without which no Common-wealth can ſtand: That <hi>Protectio trahit allegianciam,</hi> and that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is not deſirous to performe every good work to the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety wherein he doth live, doth not deſerve to have a being therein, although he were a hundred times borne in it. Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right can give no man a juſt title to be an enemy to the Society wherein he hath a being; now he is an enemy to every Society, who is not deſirous to performe every good work towards it; But God forbid that any who hath what to ſay when called to it, ſhould not be heard in the Society where he liveth and is borne. It hath been my earneſt work to intreate men to ſay in a
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:165758:32"/>Chriſtian way that which they had to ſay, and I have uſed, all the induſtry I could to bring them without partiality to it, that by the things wherein we agree, we might come to a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther light in that wherein we agree not; but I have reaped no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing almoſt but jealouſies, reproaches and ſlanders for my pains; and have been worſe rejected here, even by men other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Godly, then I have been in Forrain parts amongſt the ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Lutherans. Yet I hope that ſhall never make me weary in well doing, or vary from the Rule, whereby, as I am taught, to judge none before the time; till the ſecrets of hearts, and hidden deſigns of ſelf-intereſt be opened; So I hope the Lord will inable me never to ſhut the Bowels of pitty &amp; compaſſion; or to reſtrain the affection of prayer and ſupplication againſt any, whom I ſhall perceive to be in any dangerous error and ignorance; and the like favour I ſhall alſo deſire you to afford unto me when you look upon me in my frailtys; and if we would be but truly carefull thus to beare one anothers burdens, rather then to complain and murmur againſt each other, or to miſrepreſent each other to the publick, we ſhould find more comfort in our way then now we do. I ſhall cloſe with you in your laſt requeſt. The Lord give us a right underſtanding in all things, and grace to follow the things which we underſtand, without partiality; which is the upright indeauour,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>of your Servant in Chriſt. Joh. Dury.</signed>
               <dateline>From my Study <date>this 24. May 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:165758:33"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Reader, there is lately come out theſe ſeveral Books of Mr.</hi> Duries.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> A Caſe of Conſcience concerning Miniſters medling with State-matters, in and out of their Sermons.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Conſiderations concerning the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Engagement.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Juſt Repropoſal to humble propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> His vindication of himſelf.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> Objections againſt the Engagement anſwered.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
